The science and practice of enhancing human
performance for sport, play, and life.
Welcome
to Perform.
I'm Dr. Andy Galpin. I'm a
professor and scientist
and the executive director of the
Human Performance Center
at Parker University. Today's guest is Dr. Herman Pontzer.
Herman has a PhD in biological anthropology
and is currently a professor at
Duke University
in the area of evolutionary anthropology. In
today's show, you're gonna learn a
lot about what Herman is probably most famous for, and
that is how metabolism really works.
We talk at length, and you'll learn a tremendous
amount about how to properly think of
energy expenditure, the role that exercise does or
maybe surprisingly doesn't have
in things like energy expenditure,
body weight, body composition, and overall health. He
also does a wonderful job teaching
about how energy expenditure changes
with things like pregnancy
and other things we don't typically think of as
exercise or sport, but are highly
relevant and incredibly interesting
regarding how our metabolism and overall physiology works.
So there's a lot of practical tips here.
There's a lot of just
fascinating information.
I know you'll enjoy it. I was thrilled to
do it. I waited a long time
to talk to Herman. So with that said, please enjoy
today's episode with Dr. Herman Pontzer.
Dr. Herman Pontzer, thank you for
coming in today.
It's fun to be here.
It is a huge honor. I've been wanting to talk to you for a
really long time, even before I had a, a podcast.
(laughs)
Your, your work is incredibly interesting. Um, I'd
actually like to start with exactly your work-
Yeah.
... in the sense that,
uh, your PhD is in, uh,
anthropology from Harvard.
That's right. Yep.
Um, but you probably are most, I'd say, notable for setting
the world on fire a little bit with, um,
some interesting and controversial
takes on metabolism.
Mm-hmm.
How the body burns fat, the role of f-
physical exercise. You had a,
a series of papers come out that, um, I'd say put you on
the map, if that's a fair way to put it. So,
what is it exactly that you do? Why is a anthropologist, uh,
changing the way we think about metabolism?
That's a great question. Uh, so, you know,
as an anthropologist, I'm interested in how the human
body works and how it got this way, right?
Yeah.
So sort of an evolutionary lens on the way
the body functions. Uh, and
so coming up through my training in undergrad and
then graduate school, uh, I never
had any sort of public health or sort of, you know,
obesity research sort of interests necessarily.
I wanted to understand energy
expenditure though, because
it's, it's just sort of this... It's where the
rubber hits the road, you know?
Yeah.
Uh, any organism is, uh... You can think of
it as a strategy for turning
energy into offspring, right? That's
the game in life.
And so, uh, from undergraduate up through graduate
school, I was very interested in how the body
brings energy in and burns it off. Uh, and
you start following your nose that way, and you get into
some interesting places, because, you know,
trying to understand how locomotion burns
calories and how that relates to anatomy,
that was my graduate work.
Okay.
Uh, and then when I kind of thought I understood
that pretty well, I, I built like a...
Put together a mathematical model for predicting the
energy expenditure, you know, to, to go
walk or run a mile depending on how
your limb anatomy looks.
Right.
Uh, I felt like I understood that
pretty well, and I
thought, "Okay, let's, let's, let's expand that. Let's
think about a whole energy budget."
How does a whole, you know, a, a chimp or a human or any...
How do we bring energy in and burn it off
over 24 hours, the whole, the
whole shooting match?
And, um,
s- uh, turns out
people hadn't really been doing a lot of measurements, uh,
you know, of total energy expenditure, all
energy burned through the whole day, um,
in humans outside of like Western context. We had data
from the US or Europe. We didn't have-
Yeah.
... data from traditional contexts which
are sort of more relevant
for, you know, human
evolutionary perspectives.
Yeah.
We had no data on, uh, the other apes or that kind of
thing. And so I started this whole... The
last 20 years has been trying to, to measure
energy expenditures in these contexts
from an e- ecological, evolutionary perspective.
And then, you know, we wi- wind
up in some pretty interesting territory.
Your first book-
Mm-hmm.
... Burn, walks like through a lot of
these things, but just-
Oh, sure.
... as a starting place in the story here, um, what, what, what
is this deal with this hunter-gatherer group?
Yeah.
What did we get wrong with the paleo
diet? Like give us the-
Oh. Yeah.
Give us the real quick overview there.
So, you know, again, from an evolutionary perspective,
how do we understand our body? Well,
we are hunter-gatherers, right? Humans have been hunting
and gathering since before we were humans.
Yeah.
Right? 2 million years. Um, and
our species is only
300,000 years old. So that's, you
know... We are a
hunting ga- and gathering species. That's
the ecological context.
And so if you wanna understand how
the body works, um,
you know, California's fine, and, uh, New
York's fine, but more relevant-
Sure.
... would be a hunting and gathering context.
Uh, and so
luckily, there are still a handful of communities that are
still doing that, you know. And they're not,
they're not like time machines of the past or anything like
that, but they give us a sense of, "Okay, if
you had this lifestyle in this ecological context,
this is how the body would function."
They allow you to ask that question.
And so nobody had measured
energy expenditures
in a hunter-gatherer group before. Um, I had some
colleagues that, that were working
in northern Tanzania with a, a
community called the Hadza.
And so, uh, we went there and did
this work. And so
w- we
used this technique called doubly
labeled water, which
is this isotope tracking technique
that's a really, you know,
accurate measurement of how many...
Uh, it's actually,
um, measures how much carbon dioxide the body makes every
day. So that tells you how many calories.
It's over about a week or, or two-week period, so it's a really
good look at how many calories you're burning.
And we wrote those initial grants, uh, to go do this
project, because we wanted to document
how... Like, just the huge amount of
calories that we were sure
r- we were sure they were burning. 'Cause they get more
activity in a day than most Americans get in a week.
Right.
Right?
And so... And we were like, "Well, that's the way that
humans used t- everywhere used to live.
Let's understand what that does to the body." It's... The
calorie expenditures are gonna be huge.
Nobody's mea- measured it. It was exciting
to go do this work, right?
And so we go there to northern
Tanzania, 2009 and 2010, uh,
armed with, you know, isotopically
enriched water and-
Mm-hmm.
... the whole kit. Uh, and we do
these measurements. Um,
and we get back and we get the data
set back, um, and
we're just completely shocked, because,
you know, actually, it turns out the total energy
burned per day was no different
than folks in the US, Europe, uh, you know, s-
people sitting at their desks all day.
Uh-huh.
Like, what's going on? And, uh...
And so, you know, you have a choice
there as a scientist.
You have this model of how the world works.
It is totally crushed by the data.
(laughs)
You know? And do you stick with
the, the model
or do you f- say, "Okay, these are the
data. We're gonna follow the data and say
this, this is the observations."
Obviously, you check and make sure you didn't make any
silly mistakes, all that kind of stuff.
Yeah, I think there's a little bit of a
reckoning in your soul, right?
Yeah.
You're like, "Oh my God, our whole
project is wr-"
(laughs)
We've, we've messed something up.
That's exactly it.
Right?
Yeah.
And then you j- double and you triple and
you standardize again-
Yes. Yes.
... and the data don't change, and now...
Yes.
Yes. You know, and so what do you do? And so I
thought, "Well, okay, here we go."
I guess I'm, you know, gonna talk
about obesity now.
Yeah.
So I said... 'Cause that was this idea in
public health, of course. You still
hear it. Oh, we're so sedentary
now, which is true,
and that's bad. That's true. And, um,
and now we're not burning up as many calories, and
that's why obesity is a problem.
Well, that part turns out maybe
not to be true. And
so let's think about... You know, so I
wrote the paper and, and, um,
you know, and then all of a sudden, like you say, I'm in
this space talking to people like you.
When you say energy expenditure-
Yes.
... and you're saying things like
these people who are hunter-gatherers
in, in various parts of Africa... And
you've done that work in, in
Tanzania, in Kenya, and you've sort
of been all over.
Yeah.
And you say that it's not different than
us sitting around all day.
Yeah.
What is energy expenditure? What are you
actually talking about here?
Yes. Good place to start. So, you've got about 37
trillion cells in your body, give or take.
Just a few.
Yeah. Nobody's counting them, but you
know, it's about that. And so
every one of those cells is like a little
factory, right? It's got a
set of jobs it does. It brings resources
in. It does its thing. And
so every little factory is
burning energy, right?
And so all of that cumulatively is what we
call your metabolic rate, right?
Um, and we can think about all the
energy that you burn
over the course of...... a minute while you're on the treadmill.
We can think about it w- while you're, uh, at
rest, you know, for an hour. We can think about it over the
course of 24 hours. And so, the way that we usually
measure it is over 24 hours. Actually, we
measure it, we measure it over a week
or more, and then we take the average, sort
of per 24-hour period. Um,
and so that's your metabolic rate. And so, it's
all your systems altogether.
One of the things that people kind of
misunderstand initially
is that they think, "Oh, well, your energy
expenditure is all about how active you
are." Even if you're active,
most of your calories are being
burnt on other things.
Yep.
Your immune system, your brain, you know,
all the... you know. So, uh,
anyway, so it's, it's the full package.
It's the whole... all
the things that your bodies are doing. That's your, your
metabolic rate that we're talking about.
Mm-hmm.
You know, not the per minute cost on a treadmill, not while
you're just sleeping, but the whole thing.
Right. So if you were to say
all the calories you burn in a week, uh-
Yeah.
... some of them will be burned
just staying alive.
Yep.
Right. We, we call that generally your basal metabolic
rate or your resting metabolic rate, right?
Mm-hmm.
That's one of the components.
Yeah.
Then the calories that you burn working out-
Yep.
... which is generally, what, 5, 10%?
It depends on how much you work out. So, uh, it can be 30%
of your expenditure if you're active. Yeah.
Okay. So somewhere, um... basal metabolic rate
is generally, what, 40, 50, 60%?
Usually over half, a little over half. Yep.
Yep.
Then on top of that, you've got some
additional calories you burn from
twitching and fidgeting and like-
Mm-hmm.
That's, what, another 5 or 10%?
Well, it's hard to put numbers on that. So that's
where it starts to break down 'cause-
Right.
... it's really hard to figure
that out, right?
This, this is where you've made
your money, right?
Yeah. I guess that's right. Yeah. And
so, I mean, right now
talking to you, I'm burning more calories than I was
in the, you know, the Uber over here
chilled out zoning out. Right?
Right.
Um, and so we wouldn't call this physical activity,
but my heart rate is higher, right? My
sympathetic tone is higher, right? All
those things. And so
I'm burning more calories just by being
alert and attentive to you.
A little bit of good stress happening, right?
Hopefully.
I think so. And so, th- things like that burn
calories too, and it is actually
quite hard. One of the next things we wanna try to do is to
understand how that works 'cause that's... I think
that's where the body can really juggle
and, and, and can make space for somebody who's
really physically active to still somehow
have more or less the same energy expenditure per day
as somebody who's, who's sedentary
'cause they're juggling these sort of, you
know, these fungible things.
Okay. Tremendous. So, when you say something like
these hunter-gatherer groups and it-
Yeah.
... Hadza is the one you worked out-
Right.
... it actually doesn't really matter, right? W- We're
actually just thinking conceptually about-
Yes.
... how the body regulates energy.
Yeah.
You have that one example, but
whatever.
We replicated other places and yeah,
it's a general concept.
Right.
Yeah.
So,
when you say they have the same
energy expenditure
as us, you're not talking about energy
expenditure from physical activity.
Clearly, that part is higher.
Yes.
That's the variable you knew.
So is it... their basal metabolic rate is
higher or lower, or is it their
other... this, this NEAT or, or some
other factor? How is it
that, that total number-
Yeah.
... that total energy expenditure is the same? How are
they manipulating their partitioning
to hit the same final number?
Yeah. So, eh, I don't think it's as simple as
BMR, basal metabolic rates.
Right.
I think it's the other parts of
the awake day.
Mm-hmm.
Um, we know from... So here's where we have
to move from those studies of
folks like the Hadza and, and those kind
of ecological contexts
to, you know, places, uh, uh, s- experimental
setups where we can control things more
and then we can have a better chance at
getting exactly what's going on.
So if we move this question about
activity and expenditure
into a lab here in the US where we can control
everything, here's what we know.
If you, um, look at athletes versus
non-athletes, right? And you
give them a stress, a psychosocial stress, the
athlete will respond, uh, less.
Their, their, their bump is smaller and it returns to
baseline faster. So they've saved energy
on that stress response. Um, if you look
at, uh, things like inflammation, so inflammation is your
immune system being overly active, it's gonna
co-... we don't know how many calories it costs,
but it must cost something. And you
have less background inflammation if you are
physically active than if you're not.
If you look at things like testosterone levels
or progesterone levels or, um,
estrogen, you know, depending on male or
female, athletes, um,
endurance athletes especially, will see, uh,
reductions, not, not unhealthy, but,
you know, moderations in
levels of testosterone and that kind of thing. And
that's... those are anabolic steroid, uh,
anabolic steroid hormones. Those are building and
burning energy and there's less of it.
Uh, and so that's, we think is how
the body's kind of
cobbling together. We think about it as
an energy budget, right?
Yeah.
How do you cobble together these pieces and keep the
top line number, you know, kind of
in the same place no matter what
else is going on?
Why would we want to, as a species, keep
that top end number the same?
Yeah. Because, you know,
a s- an organism, from an evolution perspective,
an evolu- an organism should use
every calorie it can without going over,
right? If you're... if you
aren't burning all the calories
that are available
to you, well, that's... you're leaving money
on the table. You could be burning those
calories on reproduction, maintenance, repair,
anything that was gonna help you
pass your genes on, which is what
evolution cares about. So when
times are good and you're not being super active, you
should spend energy on other stuff.
When times are bad and you're going
further to get your
food and working really hard, well, now you
don't wanna just ramp up the total
calories you're trying to get.
That's, that's even worse.
Mm-hmm.
You know? So you wanna have, uh, mechanisms in place to
moderate that and keep it... and sort of
squash that down. And that, that's, I think,
conceptually why that's happening.
Today's episode is sponsored by David.
David makes protein bars unlike any I have ever encountered.
They have an amazing 28 grams of protein, only
150 calories, and zero grams of sugar. That's right. 28
grams of protein and 75% of its calories
come from that protein. This is 50% higher than the next
closest protein bar. Honestly, it's the best
tasting protein bar I've had by a mile. While
I often talk about the importance of getting one gram
of protein per pound of body weight
for things like muscle health and recovery
and the promotion of lean body mass and satiety, the reality is
that for most people, getting that one gram of
protein per pound of body weight is
really challenging.
However, David makes that easy. Their bars taste incredible
and are each packed with 28 grams of protein.
I eat one almost every day and always have two or three in my
backpack when I'm traveling, like literally
always. It probably sounds funny, but
I eat them as dessert
all the time. When you try them,
you'll know exactly what I
mean. The macronutrients, one more time, are 28 grams of
protein, 150 calories, and zero grams of sugar.
If you're interested in trying these bars for yourself,
you can go to davidprotein.com/perform.
Again, that's davidprotein.com/perform.
Today's episode is also sponsored by
LMNT. LMNT is an electrolyte drink mix
that has an ideal electrolyte ratio of sodium,
potassium, and magnesium, but no sugar.
Hydration is critical to performance, both
physical and mental performance.
Countless studies have shown that even a slight
degree of dehydration, even as small as
1%, can lead to decreases in physical output
and mental performance. We also know that electrolytes are
critical to proper hydration, which I've been
harping on for years, but you can't do that,
proper hydration, by only drinking water. You need to
get the right amount of electrolytes
in the right ratios, and that's why I'm a huge fan of LMNT.
In fact, many of you will probably remember
that I featured LMNT in my YouTube series on
optimizing hydration nearly
five years ago. I featured LMNT
in these videos
because their blend of 1,000 milligrams of
sodium, 200 milligrams potassium, and 60
milligrams of magnesium
really is unique and different than any
other electrolyte on the market
and it has great scientific support.
I use LMNT constantly, particularly when I'm
sweating a lot, and I routinely make it a part
of my clients' optimization
programs. If you'd like to try LMNT-... you can
go to DrinkL-M-N-T.com/perform
to claim a free LMNT sample pack with the
purchase of any LMNT drink mix.
Again, that's DrinkL-M-N-T.com/perform to
claim a free sample pack.
If their total energy expenditure on
both cases is the same-
Mm-hmm.
... the Hadza clearly are getting more from
physical activity 'cause they're-
Mm-hmm.
... moving all day. Why is it then
when caloric expenditure
is identical between the two groups,
the physical difference, the
body composition-
Oh, yeah.
... is, is so significantly different?
Well, I, yeah, and I think the answer, the simple answer is
the energy in part of the system is changing.
Mm-hmm.
Right? So, the reason we have an
obesity problem,
this is the kind of conclusion they're pointing to
with these data, is that obesity
is an issue of energy intake, not
energy expenditure.
Because energy expenditure's actually
kinda hard to budge.
Yep.
And I won't say, uh, people, I get people
talk about my work sometimes and say, "Well, he's
saying it doesn't matter what you do."
I see-
"There's no change."
... enormous number of misquoting of you.
Yeah.
And misrepresentation of your position.
Yeah. "There's no change at all." I
said, "Well, no.
Uh, uh, there could be some changes, but it's smaller
and s- much smaller than you think."
Right.
Um, and s- and it is true, I will also say,
sometimes there is no change.
When you g- give somebody an exercise
intervention, there are gonna be
people that you don't see any
change in at all.
Yeah.
They, they completely compensate.
Yep.
But on average, everybody compensates a
little more than anybody thinks.
Yep.
Um, now, that means exercise, ex- a- energy
expenditure's hard to budge.
Weight gain, no matter what anybody tells you, is
fundamentally about eating more than you burn off.
Right.
It really is it.
Uh, and so, um, it must be on the
energy inside.
I have seen people use your work-
Mm-hmm.
... as justification for saying things like, "See?
Herman proved calories don't matter."
(laughs)
Yeah, that hurts.
"It's not calories, it's insulin."
Yeah.
Or, "It's blood glucose."
Yeah, yeah-
Um-
... yeah, yeah, yeah.
... and, and to make it really clear, that is,
that is or is not your position?
That is not my position.
Okay.
Yeah.
Great.
It's, I- I can't see a reality of how people use
your work to get to that conclusion.
Yeah.
Um, but what you're clearly not saying is that calories in,
calories out doesn't matter, and in fact saying
it is exactly what matters.
Yes. Yeah, it's all calories in, calories
out. Now the question is,
how do you manage that or manipulate it? It
turns out, the calories out
part's not as easy to manip- manipulate
as we thought it was.
Right.
That's one, lesson one. And then, I
think on the calories in
part, why do we eat so much, you know, (laughs) that's,
that's, that's fundamentally the question.
Well, um, I think an evolutionary
perspective on that helps
too. I think working with folks like the
Hadza helps us too, uh,
because you can kinda see the, the
dietary differences between
a population that doesn't have an issue with unhealthy
weight gain versus a population that does.
Yeah.
And begin to kind of pick those apart. Now, I'm not,
you know, I'm not a nutritionist, so
be really clear about that. Uh, but I think
there's some, some clear sort of
things you can draw from that
kind of research.
Uh, I don't remember the details of the paper
offhand, it's been a decade, but I assume the Hadza were
not, uh, regulating energy intake at all.
No, they eat, you know,
they, they, they, they're not trying to, to keep their
energy intake low. They're not dieting. (laughs)
And they eat, uh, meat clearly.
Yep.
They're eating fruits, vegetables,
carbohydrates, fats, whatever-
Yeah.
... they can get ahold of. Is that correct?
That's right. It's a mixed diet and
it changes, you know,
so we can get into this, I, I love talking about paleo diet
and, and paleo fiction stuff where others-
Yeah, you pretty much crushed that. (laughs)
(laughs)
Uh, because if you live with hunter-gatherers
like I've had a chance to do,
you know, whatever story you told yourself about
what pal- hunter-gatherers eat
goes out the window within the
first three days.
Sure. They're gonna eat whatever
they can get ahold of.
Exactly, and it's gonna change day to day and
week to week, season to season. Um,
it's, the people who I work with in northern
Tanzania are not gonna eat the same thing as people who are
gonna be in the Arctic. I mean, of course.
Right.
Right?
Yeah, it-
It kinda all is obvious.
... it was very, a very thin argument.
So, to, to, to wrap abo- us up on this one, what
you're then clearly saying is
total energy expenditure between the
two groups, uh, or
in bigger, between most people then.
Yeah.
Right? Is probably a groups of people. The
individual person we're gonna-
Yeah.
... like, we'll get into that
difference, right?
Sure, sure, sure.
'Cause that's, that's, I'm also very
interested in that.
But it's, it's likely to stay the same. The energy intake
is what's regulating overall body mass-
Mm-hmm.
... for the most part. You gave an example
of something like endurance athletes having a down
regulation, and it's just an example-
Yeah.
... of something like testosterone, not
because running is bad for you-
No.
... or bad for your endocrine system, but
because as, it is a strategy
of regulating energy output, right?
That's right. That's right.
Because your energy output of your
exercise is so high-
Yeah.
... let's bring down your anabolic
energy outputs-
Yeah.
... so that we can keep that total
number the same.
That's right. And if you look at a group
like the Hadza, you know, um,
we've measured testo- well, I say we,
the scientific community have measured
testosterone levels in the Hadza.
Yep.
They're lower than, uh, your typical
sedentary American guy.
Lower?
Lower.
Right? And that's because they're doing this
moderation, we, and that, that all
fits. Um, now I can tell you, you know, if you're
worried about the masculinity or the
virility of these Hadza guys, uh, they're more badass
than anybody listening, I would wager.
Plenty of fertility I see.
Yeah. Yeah, all that, you know. So it isn't, there's no,
i- we're not at, at a clinical level.
You know, but I think what's fun is that
you can tie this in then, there is such a
thing as overtraining obviously.
Clearly.
And I think, you know, my inter-
And you will see testosterone go down is one of
the classic signs of that, right?
Yes. And so, in my, my view, it's not just you're
healthy, healthy, healthy and then you're not.
In my view, as you exercise more and more and more, you're
regulating, regulating, and then at some
point, the body goes, "Oh, boy.
We're outta room."
And now you're re- now you're overregulating, sort
of you're, you're sort of, you know,
you do get into this clinical space
where you're too low.
Yep. Yep.
But that's a sliding scale and there's
lots of healthy middle.
Yeah.
Right? Uh, and we're probably should all be
exercising more, almost all of us. Uh,
but yeah, but now you can understand it,
overtraining syndrome,
not as some weird pathology that's, you know,
it just f- happens when you fall off a cliff,
but oh, this is the body's normal
reaction and it's just taken too far.
You will see a,
uh, I can get a line of dieticians
from here to Mexico-
Yeah.
... who will tell you about how they've
increased energy intake
in highly active people and their
endocrine system has recovered.
Yeah.
Sleep has gotten better, they've felt better,
right? Because this is just-
Yeah.
... it's part of the equation.
Yep.
Right?
Yep, yep. That's right.
All right.
So, past that then, the only other thing I
wanna cover really, um,
or ask you about in this
particular topic again is-
Mm-hmm.
... the second big thing I've heard people
misrepresent your research
and your work and your first book-
Yeah.
... uh, is the fact that, okay, he's
either trying to make, uh,
comments about the first thing we talked about, or the
second one is the fact then therefore
exercise doesn't matter at all to
body composition.
(laughs) Thank you. Yeah. Uh, perfect. No.
Uh, obviously if you exercise, it's gonna be
good for your fat, for your mass.
Um, there's some evidence that if you exercise, you,
appetite regulation i- is better.
Yeah.
So actually, the energy intake side is
helped by the exercise
more so than, you know, the e- eh- the calories
expended on exercise. It might be that
the, there's appetite regulation
stuff happening. So
no. I mean, obviously a- a- exercise is good for
a lot of things, including, uh,
keeping a healthy amount of fat-free
mass, for example.
Right. So you would be an advocate of somebody
who's trying to lose body fat-
Mm-hmm.
... uh, that exercise is probably
a good activity?
Yeah. Uh, absolutely. I- it's good anyway.
In that context, here's the benefits I would think of for
somebody trying to lose weight with exercise.
I would say, I mean, I will say, I don't
think you're gonna get much
movement on the bathroom scale with exercise.
And that's not just my work,
that's decades of work
trying to do exercise interventions for people to lose
weight, and I think that's pretty clear.
Yep.
Uh, you know, you can do an, uh, a
year's worth of exercise
and the expected weight loss as I
understand it is about five pounds.
That's probably, you're probably in
the neighborhood.
Yeah.
On average.
Uh, so, you know, if you are
overweight by more than that (laughs) right?
Then, then exercise is gonna be a small
part of the solution for you.
Right.
Um,
I think the bigger benefits of exercise are
it reg- i- it's a regulatory
activity, right?
Yep.
It gets your body kind of working together the way
it's supposed to work. We're, we are
an active species, and when you take that
away, all, things fall apart.
Yep. So what is then the other side of the equation?
Like, what is the exercise not doing, uh-
Yeah.
... again, if we're, let's just
say we're-We're
only gonna classify this in the
perspective of caloric burn.
Yeah.
There's psychological well-being and
focus and moods. Okay, sure-
Yeah.
... all that is true and positive. We're in
agreement. Exercise is great.
Yeah.
Physical activity is great.
Yes.
If we're only looking at that calorie
part of the equation
for body composition, what is exercise not doing
that people think it is doing?
It's not pushing you into an e- energy deficit where
you're burning more than you're bringing in.
It's not pushing you there as, anywhere near as much
as you think it is, would be my guess.
Uh, and the bigger lever for changing body
composition is gonna be diet.
Right.
Um, you know, and so that's
whether you can... And that's
where, you know,
I think people do have a big broad range of possibilities.
Maybe low carb helps you regulate calorie intake.
Sure.
Maybe, you know,
we don't have to have any magic around insulin. You, you
could just imagine that a low carb diet might be
a good way to keep your, you from
overeating kind of thing.
Yeah.
Um,
but no, I don't think exercise
has the impact on
total calories burned and therefore energy deficits the
way that we're often sold it as having.
Let, let's put some numbers behind it.
Sure.
Uh, you, you could give some
examples here, but
if, if it helps, you can walk us through, um,
the additive versus constrained-
Sure, sure.
... stuff that you've put us together, but-
Yeah.
... i- if I burn,
let's say, two to 400 calories
in a, in a workout-
Mm-hmm.
And it doesn't matter. Let's just say it's
an accurate measure, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Who, who cares?
That's a reasonable number for people
to burn in exercise.
Sure.
You're not probably burning th- a
thousand or 1,200 very often.
Right. That too. Yeah.
It can happen. Some people, like...
But on average, the person going for a run,
exercising, lifting weights, doing a-
Yeah.
... a class at a gym, probably two to 400, 500 is, is
probably a more realistic number, right?
That's right. That's right. I mean, one way to
think about that is, uh, uh,
as a rule of thumb, 50 calories to walk a
mile, 100 calories to run a mile.
Okay.
Yeah, so-
And that's just because of
insufficiencies there, right?
Yeah, that's... Walking is just
cheaper than running.
Yeah.
Um, and my, it's bi- biomechanically more
efficient. And so, um,
you know, if you're gonna do... If
you go on a four-mile
run, you can expect you burned about 400
calories as a rule of thumb.
Yeah. And that's a 30 to
45-minute activity for
sort of most people.
Mm-hmm.
All right. So, we set the stage there.
If I'm burning 400 calories... May- may- maybe we'll
use 500, whatever makes math easier.
Yeah.
Why am I not then after a week, seven days, seven times
five, that should be 3,500 calories.
Yes.
That should be my pound of fat. How are you
trying to tell me, Dr. Pontzer-
Yeah.
... that I'm not losing that pound of fat if I
didn't change my energy intake?
That's exactly right. So,
well, first of all, I'll say that for that first week or
so, you might. You might see that initial,
uh-
On the scale, you mean.
... on the s- on the bathroom scale change.
Um, but what's happening
is, uh, over time... And again, we're still
trying to figure out how this all
works, so I'm not gonna tell you that we
have it all sorted out.
Um, over time, we know when you do these exercise
interventions, if I measure your total
calories burned per day, when I check in on you
in a couple of months, in a year,
you think you're burning 3,500 calories a week extra than
you were at baseline, but you are not.
We know this. You're burning maybe just
half that or maybe a
third of that, so maybe some people are burning the same as
they were at baseline. We see that. Uh, and so
your body's making these adjustments, and that's why
you're not losing a pound a week, because
you're not actually burning 3,500 c- extra
calories a week. Eventually, your body
adjusts that and, and reduces it.
The other thing is, it's very hard not to eat the
calories you burn. That is also just true.
Sure.
Uh, and so, you know, you say, "What if I
keep energy intake the same?"
Yep, that's right, if you do.
Very hard to do.
Okay.
What is exactly changing? Um, you can use mechanism here
or numbers, whatever is e- a best way-
Yeah.
... for you to explain this. But when you
say, "My body is adjusting-"
Yeah.
... what is adjusting to keep that
total number the same?
So, we're looking into this now, and, uh, we have a, a, a
meta-analysis we're working on in my lab, because
people have done these
intervention studies now
since the early 2000s, uh, where we, you
know... You give somebody a
dose of exercise. I know exactly
how much, how many
calories per week I've dosed you
with. I watch you
do it, and then I follow you for months
or maybe o- over a year.
And, um, typically, people are
getting, uh, you know,
something like you're talking, like, uh,
maybe 2,000 calories a
week, right? So, that's like adding
20 miles of running
to your weekly schedule.
Um, we measure them at baseline
before the exercise.
We measure them
at week... uh, yeah, month six or
maybe month 12.
And what we're finding is that the average, uh,
increase in expenditure is only about half
or so of what we think you, we
dosed you with.
1,000 instead of the 2,000.
Yeah, exactly. Um, where is the en- e-
energy coming out of?
Perhaps there... In some studies we see a
reduction in BMR, but that's not
big. The bigger one seems to be perhaps in sleeping
metabolic rate. So, if, if the study had
a, a piece where they had somebody sleeping in a
metabolic chamber overnight and could measure
that at baseline and then in the intervention, we tend to
see some changes in sleeping metabolic rate.
Um,
the other changes must be in, you know, the
waking period of your expenditure.
Now, you'd think, "Okay, well, they're just,
they're being less physically active
when they're not exercising." They're,
you know, they're taking
the bus to work instead of walking,
something like that.
Th- that doesn't seem to hold up, because we have
accelerometry data with these folks.
We know what their 24-hour
movement looks like.
Um, and the NEAT part of things doesn't seem
to be changing the way that we
would expect. So, there's something
physiological happening, I think,
um, like stress response, like immune f-
like, that we're not capturing in BMR necessarily, but
that is, is helping square the numbers.
Okay. That's actually really interesting.
I, I wasn't aware of that.
Yeah.
I was thinking of it, uh, very differently.
Hmm.
If what you're saying is their BMR... Uh, because
again, let's go back to the total equation.
Yeah.
What we're trying to figure out is what part
of that equation is changing.
Yeah.
And let's assume some percentage of people are in
fact eating more and blah, blah, blah.
Yeah.
But, uh, just as a thought exercise here, let's say
that that is not a- the case at all.
Yeah.
You got a couple of things that could be
happening. One is we know
energy expenditure
in the same form and mode of
exercise over time-
Mm-hmm.
... will go down.
So, you'll get more efficient. So, that
five-mile run that used to burn
500 calories-
Yeah.
... now might burn 450 or 75 or 490.
You can get some savings there.
Yeah, yeah. Mm-hmm.
Right? So, now you're getting
s- some small amount of
efficiency of movement.
Sure. Yup.
Okay, great.
A few calories there.
I doubt
basal metabolic rate would go down
right here.
Yeah.
But what you're saying is it doesn't
look like it does, maybe-
Yeah.
... a few percent?
We can break that one down, too. That's fun,
because if, um... You know,
the basal metabolic rate should be the kind of background
stuff your body's doing to stay alive.
I'm sedentary. I'm not breaking my muscles down
every day with exercise, and my BMR is
1,000 calories a day, just to give a number.
Now, I'm exercising all the time, my body's
doing all this muscle repair,
and I'm still 1,000 calories a day.
That's interesting.
Huh.
Right? So, w- even when you don't
see a change in BMR,
I would just put that out there, it doesn't mean
that your physiology hasn't changed.
No. O- uh, that... So, this is exactly
what I'm getting at.
Yeah.
Right? So, um... But yes, that alone, right, it should...
Your BMR should be going up. If you look-
Yeah.
... at the literature across every form or fashion,
changing basal metabolic rate chronically-
Mm-hmm.
... is a really hard thing to do-
Oh, yeah.
... independent of basically one thing.
Yeah.
There's only one thing I'm really aware of
that will change your basal metabolic rate chronically. You
can do a thousand things acutely, right?
Mm-hmm.
You could take some caffeine right now, like-
Yeah.
... but then it's gonna come right back down.
Right? In fact, your work will suggest it'll
probably go below baseline?
Maybe. Yeah. That'd be fun to track.
So, then it centers back out, right?
Yeah, yeah.
The only thing that I'm aware of that will actually
chronically enhance basal metabolic
rate is an increase in lean muscle mass.
Yeah. That's right. And, you know, I think about...
Uh, uh, we're often comparing across
body sizes, so often we're kind of
canceling that effect out-
Yeah.
... because we wanna say, "Well, yeah, you're, you had a
higher expenditure because you're..."
(laughs)
Great.
Uh, and so... And that's tacked onto what they were doing
before, the week before. We have that measurement
too. And, and sure enough, it's,
it's real simple.
You take 2,600 calories, you tack it onto what they were
doing before, and they pretty much nail
exactly what they were burning
that first week.
Yep.
Go five months forward, do it again.
And to your point, they are not back to sort of
pre-race levels. You can't, not possible.
No way.
You can't, you can't adapt 2,600 calories.
But they're below what you'd expect.
They're below that
simple let's add pre-race to race and
then get our answer.
They've... And, and the, the adjustment's
about 600 calories a day.
Okay. That's a lot.
It is a lot. And so we think that's
one way of asking
what's the most the body could change,
c- could sort of absorb?
Mm-hmm.
Um, and so that's... You know, o- one thing we talk
about in that paper is maybe that's
one estimate of that.
That's the number.
About 600 calories. So, you know, you could
add 600 calories of exercise,
you know, to your life, and maybe that would be the most
you'd be able to kind of absorb and get back to
something like pre-exercise levels.
Yeah.
Probably most... I, I don't know
if that's normal
or, or typical or whatever, but that's
what we saw in that group.
Yeah. So again, you're, you're just giving a
broad number. It, uh, as you said multiple times now,
and you've seen this in your work.
Yes.
For some people, that number is zero.
That's true, yeah.
Some people, it might be 1,000, right?
Yeah.
I- i- it's gone to there, but what you're just
saying is, like, it looks like,
as an anthropologist, as someone who likes
to think about the species-
Yeah.
... that seems to be the number where if you
train really, really, really hard,
the caloric deficit that you could kind of
hold on to for a long time
from the exercise
looks like it's capped at potentially around 600
calories. Is that, is that a fair, safe-
Yeah. Sort of the ama- the amount... The
maximum amount you could absorb, you could kind
of jug- rejuggle in your budget
is something like 600 calories based on that.
Maybe that's a little bit high, but it's in, it's in that
ballpark. It's not thousands of calories.
And would it be fair to say that that
marathon a day for
five months is the highest caloric expenditure
activity that you've studied?
Personally, yes. But that's a fun
one because, uh,
when you look at that maximal expenditure... So they
s- they did that for five months. Um,
if you look at the Tour de France, it's a higher
expenditure, but it's a shorter amount of time.
Sure, yeah.
You look at, uh, Kona Half Iron- uh, uh,
Kona Triathlon, half day, even higher expenditure than Tour
de France. And so you can begin to plot out
this nice relationship between how long
you can maintain something
and what the maximal expenditure is. And that's become-
something we're interested in, in as well.
Yeah.
And, um, the analogy is like... The analogy is, is like
running. You can sprint for 10 seconds-
Yeah, yeah. Sure.
... but you can't keep that speed
up for a marathon.
Yeah.
And so we see that across days as
well. You can burn
a lot of cal-... You know, if you think about it as like
multiples of your basal metabolic rate-
Mm-hmm.
... you can ru- you can burn about 10
multiples of your BMR-
Yep. That, that number-
... uh, for a day.
That jives a lot. Yeah.
But you come out to... So, you know, and the fun
thing is that nine months, uh,
pregnancy is the most expensive thing
anybody's ever done
for nine months. Right? So there's
this fun kind of human
biology story about how our, our
metabolic limits are shaped
by our athletic abilities, but also
by our reproductive
systems. Right? And so it's kind of a...
It all fits in there.
I can't let you get away with
stopping right there.
Okay.
I have to ask more about this
pregnancy thing.
Yeah.
If you were to look at
the, the hunter-gatherer communities-
Mm-hmm.
... right? Now,
in your head and again you're imagining
they're so physically active.
Yeah.
Um, I certainly know,
as an outdoorsman myself, a hunter myself,
when I'm out there, um,
it is... It feels like I'm burning 30,000
calories a day. Right?
Right. Yeah.
Like, you're just
gone.
Yeah.
So to frame this pregnancy thing
more appropriately, when we start getting into
some of these numbers, what
is a hunter-gatherer burning throughout the day? It's
clearly... Again, total number is the same-
Yeah.
... over here, but what is their
physical activity? Is it
2,600 calories, like a marathon? Is
it lower? And then
what do these pregnancy numbers look like?
So we can go, "Wow." Like-
Yeah.
... that... Without that
context, I think it's
gonna be hard for people to understand how
that pregnancy thing is so wild.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So, um, where to
start? So, uh, Hadza men
get, like, 19,000 steps a day.
19,000 steps, okay. So we're told here it
gets 7,000 to 10,000, right?
Yeah.
So they're getting, like-
Twice that.
... probably double.
Yeah.
Uh, and they're actually doing it rather than
we're just told to do it. (laughs)
(laughs)
Uh-huh.
Uh, women are getting about
12,000 steps a day.
Um, and then they... You know, often with
a kid on their back, um,
and th- the hard work it takes to
kind of get food
out of the... You know, often, like, they're
digging into the ground to get wild
tubers, that kind of stuff. So there's added work on top of
the steps, but the walking's the big thing.
Yeah.
Um,
but to your point, so, you know,
they're burning... Topline numbers are the
same as, as you and me.
Um, where does the... How does
that all juggle out?
Uh,
a Hadza woman, because pregnancy is so
expensive, we know from
populations like the Hadza, women
are having a kid
- and this is without birth control and they, and they wanna
have a big family, so they're not trying to re-
regulate that - they're having a kid every two
or four, two to four years.
Right? Whereas in the US,
a woman who's, who's healthy and
well-nourished, you know,
this is not recommended, but you could have... She
could have a kid almost every year.
Yeah.
That's... Her body could do that.
Irish twins, yeah.
Yeah. And so, you know, not recommended, j-
real, real clear. But, uh,
but that, that's because of the energy
availability that's there to handle
what is the most expensive thing the body
can do, which is pregnancy.
Okay. So what you're, you're
kind of saying is,
when you were talking about the, the
virality and vert-
fertility of the male side, perhaps the female side,
because their expenditure is so high-
Yeah.
... that perhaps something
physiologically is, is
intentionally lowering that fertility so that
they don't have kids too often.
Oh, yeah.
Is that kind of what you're referring to?
That's right. Yeah, the body is just-
You don't know that directly. You
didn't study that, but,
like, that's kind of the thought
trainer on here, right?
Well, and... I mean, we kinda have a
lot of... There's
fun evidence about that. So if you take, uh...
Other... In other populations where women
are doing a lot of work to go get water every
day. So these are populations
in Ethiopia, I think, but also in
Central America.
Women are... One of their t- typical tasks in a typical
day is to go and get water for the family.
Yeah.
And it's a huge amount of work.
You're walking a
kilometer to get a whole lot of water, water's
heavy, and you bring it back.
Um, and then in a couple of these studies that
are just wonderful little kind of
natural experiments-
Yeah.
... you add a, a well
in, in the village. And now mom doesn't have to
walk to go get water anymore.
And fast forward a couple of years and you're
like, "Oh, family sizes got bigger
and the time between kids got smaller."
And that's because you've taken this, uh,
activity cost and you've t- you've taken it out of their
energy budget, and now the body is able to kind of
recover after a pregnancy and be ready for
the next pregnancy faster.
Okay, makes sense. Um, it's not necessarily
a... I'm assuming you're, you're
equating for and all these studies overall
sex activity and things like that. So it's not... Like,
that's probably going down somewhat, but that's-
Yeah.
... not explaining all of this.
That, that's right. That's right.
And it's, it's, um...
No, we... These are populations where people
would love to have big families.
Yeah.
Um, and
yeah. That's, that's... The issue is, uh, a v- you
know, physiology, not behavior.
Today's episode is sponsored by AG1. AG1 is a
vitamin mineral drink with probiotics,
prebiotics, and adaptogens.
Initially, I was extremely
skeptical of AG1, as
I am with all supplement companies, but after months of
discussions with their lead nutrition scientist
and the general team at AG1, I've
been impressed by
AG1's commitment to sourcing the
highest quality ingredients
and constantly updating their formulas
to have the right ingredients in
the optimal amounts.
By now, it is abundantly clear that the gut
microbiome plays a critical
role in everything from body composition
to bone health to mental health. And the
probiotics and prebiotics in AG1
help to promote a healthy gut microbiome, improve
digestion, reduce food cravings, and increase
short-chain fatty acids, which play a critical
role in regulating metabolism
and immune responses. It's for these
reasons, and many others, that
I personally take AG1 almost every day. Now, it's of
course not a replacement for eating
whole, healthy foods, but it is a
great way to make
sure that you're plugging in any gaps in your nutrition to
improve your energy, bolster your immune
system, and just generally help promote a
healthy gut microbiome
and more. If you'd like to try AG1-You can
go to drinkag1.com/perform
to receive five free travel packs
plus a year's supply
of vitamin D3+K2. Again, that's
drinkag1.com/perform
to receive five free travel packs plus a
year's supply of vitamin D3+K2.
Today's episode is also brought to you by
Renaissance Periodization. If you wanna put on muscle
through science-backed training programs, look
no further than Renaissance Periodization.
Renaissance Periodization guides users through effective and
easy to follow strength training programs
all through their Hypertrophy app.
These programs are designed by the absolute
best in the industry, including one of my favorite
sports scientists and professional
bodybuilders, Dr. Mike Israetel. You may recognize
that name because I referenced him
and his work countless times over the years. Whether you're
looking to put on muscle, gain strength, or
both, these programs will help you
achieve your goals
and have produced results in thousands of men and
women. Renaissance Periodization
also has a diet app that is backed by the
latest science and innovation
in the field of nutrition, and takes the complexity out
of dieting, helping you achieve your
ideal body composition. If you'd like to try Renaissance
Periodization, go to rpstrength.com/perform
to save up to $50 off your subscription.
Again, that's rpstrength.com/perform to save up
to $50 off of your subscription.
So, getting back to the numbers then. You
said, uh, like, what kind of are
12, 12,000 steps a day for the females-
Mm-hmm.
... right?
And, uh, what is this difference in,
like, a Hadza female total daily energy
expenditure, and then what
happens, whether it's them or in
non-hunter-gatherers-
Yeah.
... like, what happens in terms of energy
demand during pregnancy?
During pregnancy. Yeah. So, a Hadza woman-
That's quite the claim. This is the most expensive
thing we'll ever do as a human, right?
Yeah, yeah.
Metabolically.
For nine months. For nine months, right? So, a healthy
human pregnancy costs about 75,000 calories.
Total?
Total.
Okay.
You spend most of that in the second and
third trimester. Um, and, um,
if you are a Hadza mom, you've gotta do that while also
maintaining pretty high levels of physical activity.
Uh, that does come down a little bit, just, you know, the
mechanics of foraging when you're three, in your-
Yep.
... third trimester I'm sure is hard.
Sure.
Uh, but, but yeah. So, um, I'm not sure how you wanna
break it down, but that's, you know... So,
okay, here's another fun thing, uh, and this is the
kinda stuff you learn when you start moving
your sort of field of, of
investigation beyond
a westernized, industrialized context and
start looking at elsewhere
at what human beat- diversity is all about.
There are farming populations, um, a great study
of, of, of farmers in Gambia.
This is gonna sound like a real tangent,
but it's not, I promise.
Uh, y- you've got women who are working really
hard doing agricultural work.
Their, uh, total energy expenditures
are
still kind of more or less the same as everybody
else's, but on the higher end, let's say.
Higher end of normal.
They measured them through pregnancy, and they don't
change, right? They're able to maintain, uh,
i- in that context where food is
a bit limited
and... but activity levels are high, and mom's e-
already kind of pushing her limits probably
even before pregnancy, um, it doesn't get pushed
much higher during pregnancy.
And that was a study done in the late
'80s, early '90s. Um,
and so it seems like, you know,
at... if, if
mom... the most mom can do for that nine
months is pregnancy. And even if you add physical
activity on top of that, there doesn't seem to
be a lot of room to even move beyond
that, that ceiling.
And we got... the... I'm presuming you have to partition
that to the child. That's the point, right?
Yeah. That's right. So the mo- so the baby gets protected,
baby is healthy, and mom takes the hit.
Yeah.
And
if you were to contrast that to
these marathon numbers-
Yeah.
... Tour de France numbers and stuff,
like, what? You said 75,000
total calories-
Yeah.
... for normal pregnancy.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, how much is energy expenditure
on total
differ between a pregnant female versus
a non-pregnant female?
So, a normal daily energy expenditure
would be about 1.7 METS.
Yep.
Something like that. Uh, in pregnancy, that'll go
up to about 2.2 METS in the highest
expenditures o- of a sen- for a sedentary
population. Um, we're s-
trying to figure out right now if that
changes if you, you know, have active moms in
the US, right? We don't know
the, what the results are on that yet. But that's
the, the, the expectation is that
that 2.2 METS for nine months is really
the, the maximum of what the body can do.
And that is, that is an enormous amount. Again, th- that
is more than this marathon running thing.
Hmm.
This is more than Tour de France stuff. Like,
this is a really big number, right?
Well, so if you... The guys who ran across LA to DC, they
were at 3.5 METS for that five months.
There you go.
There's your context, right?
Yeah.
Male versus female, so should be
generally higher anyways.
And running a marathon a day-
Yeah. 3.5 METS. And then Tour de France, you can get up
close to 5 METS, but it's only 28 days.
Sure, right.
Right? So that's, that's the trade-off, is, like,
duration for, for, uh, maximum expenditure.
So it's almost like you're halfway between
here, right? So you're not
short month Tour de France. You're
not five months-
Yeah.
... for this running thing.
You could run a marathon every day
for nine months
and not burn as many calories as you would
having a kid.
No, no, no, I don't think that's
right. I think-
Are they close?
Uh, I think a marathon a day is still more, but you
couldn't... You, uh... How about this?
For nine months, we think the maximum a body can
do is about 2.5 METS as max. Moms,
think about this. Moms burn 2.2, but then they have
to also eat extra to gain weight.
That's right.
So, this same study of, of
duration versus maximal
expenditure, just to kind of re- reset ourselves, the
expectation is that the longer you go, the
lower that metabolic ceiling becomes.
At about nine months, that's where moms are.
Um,
and that it kind of flattens out, and the long-term
ceiling for everybody is about 2.5 METS-
Yeah.
... is the expectation from this study.
And that means that whether you wanna
be an ultra-marathon runner training
for your next big thing, or a cyclist or
whatever, or you just wanna be super
fit and exercise a lot, you're still capped-
Yeah.
... long term at about 2.5 B- BMR.
And that's the same cap for that
mom's under, basically.
Mm-hmm.
Right? So that's the... That's what
we're talking about here.
Yeah, uh, it m- it makes intuitive
global general sense.
Yeah.
Right? If that number shakes up. So, in
the case of something like
pregnancy, because you're gonna preserve it
for the developing child, that means mom's physiology, as
you said earlier, is, is gonna take the hit.
Yeah.
Same thing happening with the
overtraining situation.
Yeah, it's the same juggling, right? It's the same
over-juggling kind of thing going on. Yep.
So that means your immune system or your
endocrine system, some metabolically
active part of your life is, is going
to have to go down.
Mm-hmm.
Hopefully that it recovers.
Yeah.
But if it doesn't, this is why you see people getting
more sick when they're overtrained.
Yes.
This is why their libido goes down.
This is why sleep
and other things go down. It's in large part
because of this energy. You can
talk about it from the hormone perspective-
Right.
... but the hormones are a response.
Yes, yes.
They're the signal because of this energy
flux being off, right?
That's how I see it, yep.
If you look at the folks that pay a lot of
attention to what's called RED-S.
Oh, right. Yeah.
I'm sure you're familiar with that, right?
Mm-hmm.
Um, how does that fold into this equation? Maybe just
walk us through a little bit, like, what
RED-S is. I know you're not a dietician.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So take care of it.
So, uh, and let's see if I can get the acronym right.
REL- Relative Energy Deficiency Syndrome.
Yeah, there you go.
I'm a simple man. And in my mind, RED-S
is, like, is just kind of
another way of talking about
overtraining syndrome-
Yep.
... basically.
It's the energy side.
It's the energy side of it, that's
right. Uh, and, you know,
one way to think about RED-S is you're not
getting enough energy in.
But the other piece of it is you can...
There are studies where they
supplement athletes and that helps, that's
great. But you can... There are
ath- athletes who won't respond to that-
Self-made, yeah.
... as I understand it.
And I think it's because... My, my suspicion is it's
because they've actually hit the energy
ceiling cap and they really can't
put more energy
through their bodies. They- they're not
able to h- to do that-
Yup.
... to take advantage of those
extra calories.
Yup.
... um, and so that's the
expenditure cap of it.
Yeah. And it's typically, when we talk about
reds, we're talking about female.
Mm-hmm.
Right? This is, uh, it's a way to describe what happens
when f- females tend to be really active and
oftentimes get really low
amounts of body fat-
Yep.
... body mass.
And then they have a whole host of things like
amenorrhea and, I mean, you name your-
Yeah.
... debilitating bones being more
brittle and breaking-
Yeah.
... and things like that.
Mm-hmm.
And so typically, you're gonna do a
combination of two things, or
one at least. You're either gonna
reduce physical activity-
Right.
... or you're gonna-
Increase the intake. Yep.
Inca- or both, right?
Yeah. Yep, yep.
Which is your typical treatment. I- i-
there's more to it, but-
That's right. That's right.
... it's actually-
But if you think about these energy caps on
that, you know, what i- what is the
ceiling that I'm working under, I think one pragmatic
thing to take away from that is, um,
if the supplementation is not helping, it's not
because you're doing it wrong.
No.
It might be because you're at the ceiling. And
then you take some training
away and you might get a kind of
less is more outcome-
Yeah.
... where you're actually healthier and
able to maintain higher
overall workloads because you're
not dealing with
downtime from being sick or being injured
or something like that.
Yeah. So in that particular case or in
other cases, when people have
felt like their metabolism is slowing down-
Mm-hmm.
... right? This, uh, a- and I've
seen this in plenty
of, uh, our high performing athletes-
Yeah.
... and non-athletes we deal with,
where legitimately
they used to do the same workout before,
eat the same things in the same-
Mm-hmm.
... relative amounts-
... and all of a sudden
progression of weight is, is
different, right?
Yeah.
Um, again, you'll colloquially call this, like,
my metabolism is slowing down.
Right.
You and I both know that's not what's-
Your metabolic speed is not changing.
Yeah.
Um, clearly this is a total
energy expenditure issue.
Mm-hmm.
What do I do about that? What do we actually know
scientifically? Can you raise-
Hmm.
... this number back up?
Yeah.
Uh, if so, how? Um,
I- I'll feed you a little bit-
Yeah.
... before we go on this one. The answers
you'll often hear are things
like, well, increase lean muscle
mass because-
Mm-hmm.
... muscle mass is active and it burns
a bunch of calories.
Mm-hmm.
What do we actually know about the
ability to... again,
it's not the right term, but how people
were gonna hear this-
Yeah.
... you know, raising our
metabolism like that-
Yeah.
... so I don't feel like
I have to eat 1,000 calories a day,
which is really-
Right.
... really hard to not gain weight?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Ugh. I mean, this is... that's,
that's the big question.
Be a nutritionist. Be a dietician
for me, please.
Be a... so yes, fine. First of
all, I would say
feeling like your metabolic rate
is slowing down
doesn't necessarily mean your metabolic rate is
slowing down. And so, um, you know,
we've measured, for example,
uh, daily energy expenditures in non-athletes, so
these are just typical folks, but
from about, you know, early 20s
till about late
50s, people's energy expenditures, daily energy
expenditures, are not really... we don't
see, like, a slowdown in middle age.
It doesn't hap- I mean, honestly. Look-
Say it again.
Yes. Your, your metabolism-
You're, you're g- (laughs)
... does not slow down in middle
age. And look, I'm-
What?
... I'm 47 and I feel like it
did too. (laughs)
Yeah.
But it doesn't. I mean, you know,
those are the data.
You and your science lies, Herman.
And here's another fun one, you know, this is another
great example. It's like the Hadza data where
you've got the data and you've got your
preconceived model and you have to choose.
Mm-hmm.
Because you don't get both, right?
You will see pretty routinely now, people
will talk about things like
bone health-
Mm-hmm.
... people will talk about muscle size-
Yeah.
... muscle strength. Uh, people will talk
about things like HRV-
Hm.
... that these things all will
decline with age. VO2 max-
Yeah.
... cardiovascular fitness.
Sure. Sure.
All of those examples
have been now shown to not actually decline-
Ha.
... as long as activity remains the same.
Yeah.
What you're also trying to tell
me, this evil lie-
Yeah.
... is that you're saying metabolism does
not slow down with age
on, on-
On average.
... on average per se.
Yeah, that's right. Yeah. We have, you know, this is
a study of 6,000 and some people.
Justify yourself, sir.
Thank you. I will. Uh, uh, so we have this...
it's actually a really fun science
story. Uh, we have a big international
consortium now of people
sharing doubly labeled water
measurements across studies.
This is the... is this the global human
metabolism database?
Yeah. The doubly labeled water database
or something like that.
There you go. Yeah.
Yes. Um, and so you've got my lab and a
bunch of others, um, all
sharing data. It's a really fun science story
that way. Um, and we've got... and
now it's, I think, it's 10 or 11,000 measurements of people
from eight days old up to people in their 90s.
So this is a full snapshot of human
metabolic diversity.
Men and women, active, inactive-
Absolutely.
... healthy, diseased, whatever, right?
Yes, yes, yes. Everybody. Um, and so we
can really say something
that we, you know, that we can stand behind about
what, for example, what, what does
metabolic rate look like over the,
the arc of a lifetime?
You published this already, right?
That's right. That's right.
Yeah, yeah.
That's... uh, it's a 2021 paper.
Life- lifelong metabolism paper-
Mm-hmm.
... or whatever. Yep.
That's right. Uh, and so, yeah,
there's some really
fun stuff. When you're born, you know...
uh, well, first of all,
one thing that you get right away, which is kind of obvious,
is that bigger people burn more calories.
Okay. Yeah. Body size, right.
Body size. Uh, men and women, when you
correct for body composition,
burn the same.
So-
Again, you're gonna have to say that
one again. When you-
Yeah.
... particularly when you correct
for lean mass.
Yep. That's right. So a typic- you know, a
150-pound man and a 150-pound woman, um,
the man might burn more calories
on average because
they'll... uh, men tend to carry less
body fat for a given size.
But now let's s- ask the question differently.
150-pound man, 150-pound woman,
both the same body fat percentage, imagine,
the expected expenditure's the s-
the e- the same.
You would, in looking at those people-
Yeah.
... you would think, in that case, the woman is a
lot healthier, leaner, because
at the same body composition, a woman
will look a lot physically
leaner-
Hm.
... than a male j- just because normal.
Yeah.
But when you equate for those two things-
Yes.
... their total expenditure
is you would not be able to be like,
that's male, that's female.
That's right. That's right. Uh, I mean, it comes back to
this 37 trillion cells doing their jobs.
And when it's the same composition
of cells, the same
fat-free mass, the same fat mass, they're all kind of doing
their thing, things like sex differences
disappear from your results. You
don't see it.
Okay.
Uh, there's a whole bunch of stuff I wanna
ask about this in terms of
are we then thinking about human capacity,
human systems', um, adaptability-
Mm-hmm.
... as,
you know, your book, your new book is-
Yeah.
... uh, wrong. But before that, to finish
our, our little story here-
Yeah.
... so we don't see in this
giant database now
using... it's all doubly labeled water.
That's right.
Not-
And I, I will say that, that we get the same
pattern with basal metabolic rates.
So we have two modalities giving us the same answer, so
it isn't like, oh, this measurement-
I see.
... has a problem. J-
just to be clear, because that's always
what... the follow-ups-
It's actually su-
Right.
That's more interesting, right?
Yeah.
'Cause now you're using two
different methodologies-
Yeah.
... for that same measure and they're
both at least aligning-
That's right.
... overlapping in a pretty high correlation.
Yes, yes, yes.
Okay.
So no differences between the sexes.
Generally no differences past, uh,
what, probably age 20, 25? When is that-
Yeah. I mean, you kind of... you know,
biology doesn't take hard corners, right? Th-
things kind of mellow out. So
around 20 to 25, somewhere in there, you hit
kind of your, your adult rate-
Yep.
... and then you're s- you're just
rock steady until
late 50s, early 60s, something like that, and then it
begins to decline again, which is interesting.
Mm-hmm.
'Cause we know that that's, that later
age, uh, is when things like
diabetes risk, heart disease risk, dementia risk,
all these things kind of inflect up-
Yeah.
... after 60
and your metabolic rate's inflecting
down. And th- these are all
body mass, body composition controlled, so it isn't
just sarcopenia, 'cause that happens too.
Yep.
Um,
and so I think we're seeing cells-
Loss of muscle. Yeah.
... slow down. Yes. The, we're seeing
cells slow down. We're seeing
the body slow down and that's related to, I think,
um, this increased disease risk.
All right. So I got one question on the each
side of the age spectrum.
Sure, sure, sure.
Uh, I know you got some new work... I
think you got a new, uh,
NSF grant for doing a bunch of stuff
with adolescent girls.
Mm-hmm.
Right? So you've got some experience in the, the
children's side of the equation-
Yeah, yeah.
... as well as now past 50. So two-part
question. One of them is-How much
higher is, generally, energy expenditure
when it is peaked, right?
Yeah.
I, uh, I presume it peaks at
puberty or close to it.
Oh. It peaks at... Size-corrected expenditures peak
when you're one years old. That's your-
Boom. You-
We've all peaked too soon.
Yeah. (laughs)
That's it.
(laughs)
So, you're... You lied to us earlier. It does go down
with age. After one, it goes down.
That's right.
You're right.
To 20.
Yeah. Exactly.
One to 20. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Uh, yeah. A little baby,
you know, one, one-year-old infant, um,
is... Their cells are just super
busy, right? And
you can see that in the calories they're
burning. Now, look, they're also
tiny, so total calories a day is
not impressive.
Right.
But when you correct for body size,
it's 50% higher.
Yeah. It's a lot.
And if you could sh- if you could shrink
an adult down to that
size, the baby's got, burning 50%
more calories than
the adult.
Yeah. Well, I mean, it's turning over its
entire skeleton in a year.
All those-
Like e- everything is, is really ramped up.
Yes. Yes. Yes.
But when you get into your teenage years, how much
higher is that expenditure as...
You know, whether it's teen or tw-
whatever that peak.
Yeah. You're coming down, you're coming... And so, you
know, it's sort of a, a, a sort of a glide
path. And so, you know, by the time you're 10,
you're probably around 20% higher-
20%.
... than you would be as an adult. And then slowly,
it's gonna kind of come down. Um,
that's, that's the kind of ballpark. 20 to 30% higher.
So, when your teenage kid comes home
and eats the entire fridge,
yeah, that's real.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, yeah.
(laughs) And that's because, you know, their
metabolic rate's just higher just
because their bo- their still developing.
And do we know what part of the metabolic equation that's
coming from? Is it all of it? Do we know?
So, we... Again, we see the same
pattern in BMR.
That doesn't really answer the question 'cause your
BMR is all your organs playing around.
Yeah.
So, we don't know which organs are doing what.
So, the brain is super expensive.
Um, even in an adult, the brain burns
300 kilocalories a day.
Yeah.
Um, whether you're dumb or not-
(laughs)
... as I like to remind my students.
Actually, probably more if you're
more dumb, right?
(laughs)
It just feels that way.
More dumber. Yeah.
Yeah. Uh, so, you know, um, when you're a kid, it's
probably even higher than that because
not only is your brain doing its
expensive thing of thinking and-
It's developing.
... regulating. It's developing.
Yeah.
Uh, and so all the organs are probably doing
that. We don't know... Like,
uh, next, another frontier kind
of thing to do-
Yeah. Well-
... is figure all that out.
... I ask that because we
colloquially will hear things like, "Well, oh, man.
Yeah. I played all these sports as a
kid and so I was lean, but now I'm not
playing sports anymore."
Yeah.
And so people will tend to justify that
15 to 20-pound gain in their early 20s-
Yeah.
... as, "Well, I just stopped playing sports anymore,"
and then they rush back into the gym.
Yeah.
Don't often see a lot of results-
... and then partake in-
Yeah.
... sedentary activity for the next 20 years.
That's right.
So, how are we thinking about
that incorrectly?
Yeah. Also, I mean, I think that
the higher expenditure that you had as an
18-year-old, you were at the
wonderful tail end of this elevated metabolic
rate that you get for free-
Yeah.
... just from d- your development. Um,
you hit 21, 22, 23, and that goes away, you know, and
that usually coincides with a lot of life
changes. You get your first job, et cetera,
et cetera. It all collides.
Yeah.
Um, but yeah. I think the big bump that you thought
was 'cause you were playing baseball
is actually because... Maybe the bigger bump is actually
just 'cause your body was still developing.
Yeah. So, it's almost really a combination.
Yeah.
You're le-... Generally, people are way less
physically active post-high school.
For sure. Yeah.
They're probably also maintaining the
same nutritional habits.
Yes.
(laughs)
Yeah.
Intake. So, it's, it's all of those things.
Yeah. That's right. That's right. And then,
you know... Look, stress is an
issue. Sleep is an issue. All these
things that push us-
Yeah.
... to eat more.
Right? I mean, all of a sudden, I'm
stressed out all the
time, and I find myself eating more than I did
bef-... You know, the things like that.
Of course. Yeah.
And, um,
that, that more than some kind of global change in your
me- metabolic rate in your 30s is, is
kind of what's, I think, really pushing
things around for people.
Yeah. Then let's go to the other end
of the age spectrum.
Yes, sir.
Now, what happens? And I am... You know, it... Okay,
well, I'll say this. It's fair to say,
if you want to think about it this way,
your metabolism slows down
past 20. Okay?
Mm-hmm.
They have that big bump when we're 10 or
15, 12 years old, whatever.
It does start to glide down, as
you're mentioning.
Mm-hmm.
It levels out
mid-to-early 20s.
Yeah.
It holds on for the next 30 or 40 years.
Mm-hmm.
So, you can blame those pounds you
gained as a 20-year-old
on it.
Sure.
But you can't gain those pounds you
gained as a 40-year-old-
Yes.
... most likely on it, but it will now start to
decline, even as you're saying
when you correct for maintaining muscle mass.
Right. Which we know is harder
past 50s. Yeah.
Really, really hard, right?
Yeah.
So, let's just say you were able to maintain that
thing. Do we know what is happening
both mechanistically as well as, again,
what part of the equation-
Yeah.
... post-50, if it's not-
Mm-hmm.
... loss in muscle? Because if you were
to ask me right now-
Yeah.
... I would say, I bet it doesn't happen as
long as you hold your muscle.
Oh. Yeah.
That would've been my guess.
Yeah. So, um,
I don't know that it's that easy. Uh-
Damn it.
Yeah. I know.
(laughs)
Because the... Again, this is paired with basal
metabolic rate measurements-
Science
is supposed to be easy.
Is- is... It's more fun when it's not, but I agree. It's
not... Yeah. Uh, the stories are simple.
(laughs)
You're a teacher. You're a storyteller.
Yeah.
Supposed to be easy. Come on, doc.
Yeah. Yeah. So, um,
so it could just be, you know,
that you lose muscle mass and your
metabolic rate goes down for that.
Yeah.
But we correct for that, and we still see it.
Oops. Okay. Next explanation.
Um,
if you do basal metabolic rate measurements
along with this, which we
have in that same dataset, you see that,
you know, for a given
fat-free mass, so for a given organ sizes, you... Whole
organ size and muscle mass, the same.
Metabolic, basal metabolic rates
even at rest are lower
pa- post 60. And so the only way you can get
that mechanistically, uh,
is for the cells themselves to
be slowing down.
Um, now you're asking a different
question, I think.
Mm-hmm.
Related but different, which is if
I'm physically active,
and one thing that'll happen is I'll keep
my muscle mass up maybe.
But the other thing that might happen is, um, again,
exercise is a regulatory behavior.
Yup.
Right? And I'm signaling to my body to keep
going and, you know, it... I don't... That's
a very hand-wavy way to talk
about it. But there's something about
that regulation of activity
that might keep all your cells more active.
Yeah.
I... Uh,
okay. I'd love it. Let's test that. I mean, I
think that's possible. Uh,
I don't think we would know that
for sure right now.
Generally, we associate aging
with inefficiency
at the cellular level.
Yup.
Right? So, you're losing
either actual cell mass. Uh,
things are dying.
Mm-hmm.
Breaking off, going down, or they're becoming
hyper-inefficient, more leakage.
Yeah.
Which I would think would actually then make
energy expenditure higher.
Mm-hmm.
What am I missing here?
I think
you could have two things happening. You can have
inefficiencies and just lower output overall.
Right? I mean,
again, the only way you can make
the math work
on these measurements of expenditure, and you get it from both
modalities, so it's not just a methods thing-
Yeah.
... is that it has to be the case that
a liver ce-... You know, uh, let's just say, to pick
an organ, I don't know if this is
the right one. A liver cell in a
70-year-old burns
fewer calories every day than the liver
cell in a 40-year-old.
Yeah.
And
there's... It kind of has to be that.
Yeah.
Um,
now is it, is it the liver, or is it a different
organ? And how... What's the...
That's the interesting set of questions.
Yeah. But in... One of them-
Yeah.
... is... It's gonna have to be one
or a combination.
Yeah.
Something has to be changing.
You think this is a function of
looking at, I would not say exclusively, but
primarily cross-sectional data-
Hmm.
... uh, versus having, you know, more longitudinal
thi- things like that. Is that-
No. That's a f- that's a fair point. I mean, these are big
cross-sectional studies. Um, I don't think
you could... I, I think there has to be a longitudinal signal in
there to see the big data trends that we see.
Um, but it is true for all sorts of obvious reasons that
we don't have data from somebody who's 40
and then 50 and then 60 and then 70. We, um... That
would be a study that's still happening
and started 40 years ago, right? We
don't have that yet.
Yeah. But s-... I mean, jeez, we
should, right?
I agree.
We started, right?
I agree. I agree. And, and we're, um...
That would be something we'd really, be
really interested in, is sort of, you know, gets you at 55,
gets you at 60, gets you at 65, and see.
What is the longest that we do
have? Do you know?
Do we have any two-year studies? Do we
have any five-year studies-
Yeah.
... that have-
We do. We have two and five-year studies here
and there. Small ones, uh,
but not-... that I know of in that critical
post-60 age group. The ones I know of
are in people's sort of, you know, prime
adult years. And that's interesting. There,
you find individual differences
are pretty static. So, if I
measure you today and I
see that you have a high metabolic rate, and I
measure you again in two years, I'll see
that you have a high metabolic rate again.
Mm-hmm. Mm-hmm.
And it kinda... It even, even independent of what you
report anyway is lifestyle change.
If you're slow, you're slow. If you're fast,
you're fast. Now, the good news
is, it doesn't seem to have a big impact
on whether you've gained weight or lost
weight in the intervening years.
Yeah.
So, that's another kind of myth, right? People think,
"Oh, my metabolic rate's high. That's why
I keep the weight off." Probably what you are
experiencing is a better relationship with food-
Uh-huh.
... that you aren't being pushed to
overeat the same way
that somebody who says, "Oh, I have a
slow metabolic rate," is
maybe more food-focused and is... has a different
relationship with food. And is, is having
a hard time that way. It might not be meta-... In
fact, it's not metabolic rate. I'll say
that. It's... Right? And the way...
Here's, here's my metaphor for
that. You walk into a bar, you wanna
play some darts, right?
And they've got the dart boards
hung on the wall
and you're throwing your darts at the wall.
You don't know if that dart board is
hung a little high
or hung a little low. You just know
you're trying to hit it.
And that's what your body's doing with
expenditure and intake.
It doesn't know if you happen to have a little
bit of a high metabolic rate
or a little bit of a low metabolic rate. It's just trying
to balance the budget and hit the center
of the bullseye, right? So, if I s-... If I came and said, "Oh,
yeah. Your, your dart boards are hung a little
high," I'm still gonna find that the darts are
stuck around the, the center-
Yeah.
... because people are still aiming at
the center. They're not
aiming at what they... At, you know, some
global middle dart board height.
Yeah.
They're naming it that one, and
that's how your body
works. You're aiming at that metabolic rate. And so,
if you're high, you're high, that's
fine. And... But, but missing the bullseye
and gaining or losing a little bit of weight
is gonna be independent of
if the guy next door is aiming at a
slightly lower dart board.
Yeah. So, if you take the person who
says, "I eat all the time."
Yeah.
"I'm constantly stuffing my face. I
never gain weight."
Yeah.
And you contrast that with a person who feels like they're
doing the opposite, what you're saying is
most likely,
that energy intake for the person that feels
like they're stuffing their face
is probably not as high as they think?
Yes. And vice versa, the person who says that
they're not eating a lot, uh, doesn't
feel that they are, probably is
eating more than they
think. And that's, you know... We've known that for a
long time, that people under-report.
Yeah.
Sometimes they over-report, but usually
they under-report, um,
and there's all sorts of obvious reasons about that.
That's not intentional. Nobody's... You know.
No, no, no.
I'm not saying people are lying.
That's not the point.
You just... People have a hard time
tracking what they do.
Yeah. I would say, in my experience, the people
who feel like they're the former,
the "I can eat anything I want," they're-
Yeah.
... they'll... They end up going through really
long periods of not intaking food.
Yeah.
So, they'll be like, "Oh, yeah. I ate a
whole pizza last night."
And you're like-
Yeah.
... "Oh, great." And then they had a
yogurt for breakfast.
Right.
And then they had a lunch they had, and
you're like, "Oh." So, actually-
Exactly.
... it... You feel-
... like you're feasting all the time-
Exactly.
... where the other folks are way more
consistent about their food intake.
Mm-hmm.
So, it feels like... And clearly,
there's more to it-
Yeah.
... than this. But, um, that's been my
experience of being like-
Yeah.
... they actually don't eat that much.
You just go through waves-
Yeah.
... of-
Yeah. That makes sense.
... eating enough.
Yeah. Totally.
Do people tend to be more physically
active, whether it's exercise or
activity
in periods of short caloric surplus? So,
if I eat a whole bunch-
Oh, that's interesting.
... more this weekend, am I gonna be
more active next week?
Huh.
I don't know
any data on that.
That, that's a nice prediction.
You could imagine
sort of evolutionary reasons that those
mechanisms would exist.
Yep.
Uh,
good question. Yeah. I don't know.
'Cause then we don't know the
opposite, I assume, as well,
right? So, if you pull calories a
little bit this week-
Yeah.
... uh, are you gonna be... 'Cause you hear people
say these things, right? "Man-"
Yeah.
"... if I pull calories down, I just...
I, uh, I don't move."
That one seems, you know, the fatigue response and, you
know, and esp-... We know that if you
really crash diet, your basal metabolic rate
can go down as a response.
Oh, sure. Yeah.
But you're not talking about... You're talking
about something smaller than that. Um,
yeah. I... Gosh, I don't know. It seems like a really easy one
to measure, and maybe people have done it, but I
can't think of a study that's looked at it.
Today's episode is sponsored by Eight
Sleep. Eight Sleep makes smart
mattress covers with cooling, heating, sleep tracking,
and more. I've personally been sleeping
on an Eight Sleep mattress cover for years now,
and it's absolutely glorious.
I love it so much that I hate
traveling away from home
because it means I can't sleep on my
Eight Sleep Pod 4
Ultra. As you'll hear me talk about endlessly on this
podcast, there really is nothing you can do
that makes more of an impact on your
health and performance
than getting tremendous sleep. And getting great sleep
requires having your body temperature
drop a couple of degrees at night,
and that's hard to do
on your own. The Eight Sleep has been
a game-changer for me
because I run hot at night, or as my
wife calls it, I'm a
furnace. If I don't have something like
an Eight Sleep helping me
cool down, I'll wake up in the middle of the
night overheating and not
feeling great. This is something I've
also found in many of the people that I coach,
especially those who are really physically
active. The Eight Sleep Pod 4 Ultra has two
times more cooling power, yet is
virtually silent, and it has
high-fidelity sleep tracking
and even has snoring detection that will
automatically lift your head a few degrees
to improve airflow and stop your snoring. If you'd like to
try Eight Sleep, go to eightsleep.com/perform
to save $350 off your Pod 4 Ultra. Eight
Sleep currently ships to the
US, Canada, the UK, select countries in
the EU, and even Australia.
Again, that's eightsleep.com/perform. I'm gonna take
what feels like a pretty big left turn.
Okay.
And I'll say it this way.
I generally have had more disdain
for the world of anthropology than
I have had love.
(laughs)
All right. Okay, okay.
It's not the work of the scientists. It's generally
the, the media and the interpretation-
Okay.
... is, is not your guys' fault, right?
Mm-hmm.
What I'm getting at is the natural fallacy.
Oh. Yeah.
And so,
I always have a hard time
getting through things like,
okay, what can we learn from
anthropology? What can we learn from
looking at culture
and looking at
ancient humans and how things
(soft thump)
... that matters without making the
natural fallacy?
Yeah.
Uh, I, I feel like you've done a
really good job of that
now, in our conversation as well as
over your career.
Mm-hmm.
Um, so
how, how do we think about these things properly,
getting the best out of studying ancestors-
Yeah.
... and anthropology, and if, if that's even
biological anthropology-
Yeah. No, that's-
... and then not making natural fallacy?
No, that's right. So, I think the value...
Let's start it this way.
The value of looking at a broad sweep of
cultures, in general, is that you're gonna
capture more of what our bodies can do
and more of how our bodies respond to changes
and differences in lifestyle-
Yeah.
... and ecology and environment, all these
things we're interested in.
But we only have a really narrow view when we only look
within the US, for example, or within, you know,
uh, urban centers in the, in the industrialized world,
right, where most research happens, by the way.
Um, so I think looking across cultures give us
a real sense of, of what real
biological diversity looks like, how, uh,
interactions with environment look like,
how that interplay happens.
And then,
the evolutionary perspective is,
it gives you a
kind of working hypothesis, a working model
f- for, for expecting how the body will work, how it will
respond, what the body is trying to do.
The body is not trying... You know, your, your body isn't
evolved to make you look great for the beach.
Your body isn't evolved to lift... you know,
to, to be a massive bodybuilder necessarily, or whatever
it is that you're trying to accomplish.
W- understanding what the body's kind
of organized toward,
the organizing theory of the body, which
is evolutionary success,
I think helps you make sense of
the physiology. Why
does my body adapt to physical activity the
way it does? Well, because
we are a physically active species and have
been for two million years. Um,
and so, you know-... uh, w- our entire
physiology is organized around that.
You take that away, you have problems, right? So, I, I think
that's the advantage. It isn't to say, "Oh,
a hunter gatherer lives this way,
therefore I'm going to
cosplay like a hunter gatherer-"
(laughs)
"... and be healthy." I mean,
that's silly, right?
Right.
That's goofy.
I'll give you a couple of direct examples.
Yeah.
I think that was great, by the way. That was
actually really helpful. When you hear
justification of a particular methodology, it
doesn't matter, diet, exercise-
Yeah.
... psychological,
uh, emot- relationships.
Yeah.
Like, you, you pick how humans interact.
You could fall back to basically any
time point, find some
previous part of our history in
which people did it-
Yeah.
... this way and justify it, right? This is
the natural fallacy of, uh, I skipped
over. I know you know, but
is the idea that just because it is natural,
then therefore that is correct.
Right. Yeah.
Right? And there are a lot of things
that are natural that
we don't wanna do anymore, right?
Yes.
We don't have to list them.
Yeah.
But you can imagine
ancient humans did some activity in a certain way that
we don't wanna do anymore as a culture.
Yes.
You see? That's not okay.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right?
Fill in the blanks, folks, if you,
if you want there.
Cannibalism's a fun one.
Okay, great, right?
(laughs) Yeah, you can find a popula- y- there's
documented evidence in the past
of people, different populations,
uh, who practiced cannibalism. Now,
why and how, those details are an interesting
question. But, um, nobody would advocate
now
that that's a great thing we oughta be doing.
I'm sure somebody would.
Yeah.
I'm sure somebody would, right?
The world's a crazy place. But most folks
are not gonna wanna do that.
So, if the natural fallacy exists, then
why does it matter at all
that we study all people?
Oh, yeah, yeah, yeah. No, I mean, again,
that, that gets me back to this diversity
thing. Because if you wanna know
what, uh, a really physically active day in,
day out lifestyle looks like
or, uh, you know, how our bodies juggle those demands, well
then let's go and ask that question. Let's go
find populations that are really
physically active.
Let's w- find ones that are sedentary. Let's
find ones that eat a really
high carb diet. Let's find ones that eat a
really low, you know, high
meat diet. Um, and that's a way of asking about
that diversity. I think you also
learn some other interesting things. You learn
about local adaptations in some cases
that you otherwise would, would miss. Um,
but, uh, but I, I think that's the
advantage is, um,
in terms of, in terms of when we br- wanna
bring it back home to a health
context, right?
Yeah.
What we're gonna learn about how we're
gonna fix our own lives today.
That's it. You're learning about
these sort of, th- the diversity of human
experience. And you can pick and
choose the lessons from that, not in a
lateralistic fallacy kinda way, but in a,
hey, they've tried it that way for...
and, and this is how
they result. Th- this is how their body results from that.
I can bring that home. Great example. Um,
physical activity we know is important, uh, for lots of
reasons. But like, how much should you get?
Right? That's a fair question to ask.
Mm-hmm.
And it turns out that if you, um, look at how much,
uh... This is just a fun little comparison.
If you look at how much, uh, physical
activity folks get, um,
in a, a nice study that was done in, in
Scotland. Uh, it's, uh, where was it?
Glasgow. It's, it's gl- in Glasgow.
These Glaswegian mail carriers... All
right, this is a fun one.
Uh, you have folks who are carrying
the mail every day
getting 17,000 steps a day. You have
folks who are in the
office sorting mail, and they're not
getting the steps.
And you ask, "Who has the best health
outcomes?" And it's all National Health
Services up in the UK, so it's all kind
of controlled that way.
The real big difference here is
how active you are.
The folks who are getting the s- the
17,000 steps a day
are, turns out, really well protected
against cardiovascular disease-
Yeah.
... and all these things.
Well,
how d- how do we understand that? Well,
it turns out, if you look
at, you know, traditional groups around the
world, that's kind of the
sweet spot of where people are getting their
activity. That's how much they're getting
in a hunting and gathering context or a
farming context. It matches up.
And so, that's, you know... Not that those
mail carriers were thinking, "Gosh, I wanna
make sure I get as many"-
Sure.
... "steps as a hunter gatherer today."
Th- that's where we can learn something from
another cultural context, you know, a non-industrialized
context, and, and it helps make sense of
the practical things we can do in our own
lives here. We don't have to act
like hunter gatherers. That's not the goal.
The goal is to, to learn.
Yeah.
You and I are gonna focus on physiology-
... metabolism and exercise.
Mm-hmm.
Great. But
you can find these same examples in
cultural-
Yeah.
... in relationship, in how people
interac-... Like-
Yeah.
... we're just gonna focus on this aspect of it. But I
really think it's important that people
extend that thinking out to this is all of
how we behave as a species-
Yeah.
... that can go there. So, with the,
uh... I don't know if that was stuff in the UK Biobank,
but w- in the Glasgow, uh, example there-
Yeah.
... you're highlighting another
positive role of physical
activity and exercise-
Mm-hmm.
... but just not from the
caloric expenditure.
Yeah.
Right? That... I mean, that's kind of
what you're saying is-
Yeah.
... you're not denying and suggesting
that so many people
and so many (laughs) magazines-
Yeah.
... and articles have said that
you're saying.
There are plenty of physical activity
benefits, it's just-
100%.
... perhaps not from the caloric
expenditure side of the equation.
That's right.
Right, right. So, I just want to triple,
quadruple down on what you don't,
don't say.
(laughs) Right.
But getting back to this. How do we then
decide which of these learnings
from anthropology-
Mm-hmm.
... that we choose to take, like physical activity, but then
we don't choose to take the cannibalism one?
Right.
Well, uh, that gets to this, uh, question of,
you know, biology can tell us
how things work. Cultural studies can tell us the
diversity of what possibility spaces are.
You know, but then it, it all ends up... You still have
the hard decision to make yourself as in
what, what are my principles-
Yeah.
... what are my, uh, you know, guiding,
uh, ideas, and, and how do I bring
this into my own life?
So, um, that's why you're probably not
gonna bring cannibalism in.
(laughs)
But you might wanna exercise.
Speak for yourself.
Yeah, fine. Uh, you know, and I thi- I think there's also a
broader importance here, and that is I think
we reduce
a lot of how we study the natural
world and study ourselves
down to
what's the next thing I'm gonna do to, to, to
tweak my life, to give myself
more energy, better health, whatever. Those are all
important things to have. We should all want
to maximize our time here, absolutely.
But
there's a broader question, which is, how
do we understand the world?
How do we understand ourselves? How
do we understand
everyone around us?
Um, and you're not gonna get
all those answers with blinders on, narrowly focused on your
neighborhood and your immediate ar- area.
Mm-hmm.
You're gonna get those answers, I would
argue, by casting a pretty
broad net, asking what's going on around the world,
even in different species. But, you know,
let's keep it to our species for a moment,
asking those questions about
what happens in different cultures and different contexts.
And, and I think there's a richness there, um,
that actually does improve our lives in ways
that are harder to measure. Um,
but that, you know, uh, we often
wanna reduce things down
to the bottom line, to the health
nugget, to the biohack.
Yeah.
And, okay, I get it. But there's a broader thing
here that I think is valuable.
Right.
Very... Could not agree more. Really well
said there. How much do we know
about the variation?
And let's just stay with our wheelhouse here, of
something like energy expenditure-
Mm-hmm.
... among other,
uh, older forms of lifestyle, if you will. So,
clearly you've spent time in Africa-
Mm-hmm.
... and I don't know if you've gone
to Central America.
But how much variation do we know
exists between
Southeast Asia cultures, European,
Scandinavian, and other ones?
I assume you think your findings with the
Hadza group would extend to
everyone else. But what do we
actually know, if any-
Yeah.
... about other groups?
Great question. So, now we have this big, uh,
global database that we're putting together
has allowed us to kinda ask that question, which is
really fun. And so, we've got, um...
In the latest iteration of it, I think we've got
35 populations from around the
world.But between those genes are lots of stretches of DNA
that, as far as we can tell, don't do anything.
And because of that, you don't have evolutionary pressures
keeping them the same. They tend to vary more.
And they var- vary in a random way,
and so they create
noise, let's say, in your genome. Now, the
random processes that create
noises in one population are
unlikely to be the same
as they happen in another population. So
those random, meaningless
bits of noise in your genome actually
become a nice fingerprint-
Mm-hmm.
... for where your recent ancestry is.
Because the same random things that happened in
Scandinavia probably didn't happen
in Southeast Asia.
And so,
that's what a company, a retail genetics
company, is doing. They're looking
for those kind of meaningless... Actually, it...
The more meaningless, the better.
Yeah, the noncoding stuff, right? Yeah.
The noncoding stuff. And so, um,
yeah, so that's funny because then I think it... Those tests
are, I think, are really fun to play with.
They give you the sense that those genetic differences
are big and meaningful when, in fact, the
reason they work is that they're not
meaningful (laughs)
By definition.
Yeah.
We don't yet know what... Uh, that
they're doing anything.
Exactly. Yeah. That's right.
How do we distinguish, though? How do we draw that line?
How... When you said recent ancestors.
Hmm.
Well, that's another thing. So we know now, uh, that, uh,
you know, people have been mixing and moving
globally forever. So there are no, uh,
you know, sort of genetically isolated
pure populations, and,
uh, everybody intermixes with everybody.
That is just the truth.
Um,
and so
I couldn't use, for example, I would have a hard time... Uh,
let, let's say it this way, those little, uh,
random noise signals that tell me
I'm from Scandinavia
or s- or Southeast Asia, those only work 'cause recently
we, we measured a bunch of people from those
places, and we know what that noise
looks like there.
Right.
But check back in in 100 years, and it might be
different, right? 'Cause it's gonna keep
on churning. This, this churn is gonna keep on happening.
It's been happening for 20... It's... For
200,000 years, and that's gonna keep on
sort of mixing it up.
How good would you
call our current
database
of genetics across the-
Mm.
... the variety of cultures?
We know it's hugely uneven, right? Uh, the
most data we have in terms of, you know,
UK Biobank or GenBank or any of these
big databases, or for that matter, the retail
space of, uh, you know, the, the-
Yeah.
Those are all, um,
wealthy, largely white
populations and countries. Not entirely.
There's, you know, there's
fair... The people work very hard to get coverage as
far as everywhere they can get it.
But just in terms of the bulk of
the numbers, yeah.
I think the more recent data suggests that still,
to this point, 90-plus percent-
Yeah.
... of genetic data is on
white Caucasian.
That's right. That's right. And what we know
is that when we go... We can talk about this next.
When we do a study of, uh, you know,
what, what gene variants predict height-
I, I would love for you to go into
this. Yes, please do.
Yeah. What gene variants predict height?
What gene variants predict
cardiovascular risk,
disease risk? What gene variants predict
an... Pick your trait. When those studies are done in
the UK Biobank with a largely white
population, it turns out they're not
what they call portable.
I can find those same gene variants anywhere else because,
again, populations sha- shares these variants.
But it turns out they're not
predictive over there anymore.
Totally.
Oops.
Right? And so, um,
yeah. It's a, it's an interesting time to
be alive, right? Because
I remember in the '90s as an undergraduate, the
human genome hadn't been published yet.
Right.
We were in the
kind of the late stages of this
reckoning about, uh,
racial diversity and the fact that race is
a, is a cultural construct
that has, of course, important biology, uh,
embedded in it, and, and actually
racism itself can create biologies. I mean,
so there's a whole... But
we understood that, that race is
not a biological
category, it's a cultural category.
We understood, uh, it was a reckoning about sex differences,
it was a reckoning of all these things. And
we were ready, I think we were poised
to do the next thing, which is to get down
to the genetic level, and then we had the human
genome published, and we're still
not... We haven't... It hasn't... That
pro- it's a promise unfulfilled because the
gene, the genome work has gone
in a kind of a different direction.
Um, I think we still don't really reckon with diversity in
the ways that, that we probably ought to.
Well, you could explain a lot of
things here, but
one thing of note
is I don't think many people have really gotten past,
or the awareness has gotten out about
what I call the one-to-one gene fallacy.
Mm.
Which is an entire human genome, the promise
of it, the direct or indirect-
Yeah.
... was that, "Well, we'll sequence
every human gene-"
Yeah.
"... and because one gene equals
one physical trait-"
Yes.
"... we'll then know everything about you."
That's exactly right. Yes. That's a great way to go with it,
too, because the promise was, "I'm gonna n-
be able to sequence your genome, and I'm gonna
know everything about you."
And it didn't happen. And now we know
that it will never happen.
It won't happen.
The numbers are astronomical.
They're astronomical, and
environment has, has too big of a role.
Right.
You know? In a lot of traits, it has a
very dominant role, and in every
trait, it has some role.
And so, uh,
it's, it's... You know, it isn't that
you have three genes
and the versions you have of those
determine how h- how tall you get.
There are at least 10,000 genes
for which we know
if you have variant A or variant B, you're gonna be a
little bit taller, a little bit shorter.
And you add up all those over 10,000, and I
might know something about your height, but then I
also have to know your environment
'cause I only know about half the story with the
genetics, right? So it's a complicated system.
Well, if we wanted to be predictive about things,
it's... We can understand it at a kind of
broader level and just say, "Look, we have to understand
the interplay of environment and genetics
for each trait individually,
how they work."
That's, that's the better way in to
understanding why your
physiology is different than mine, or why this
athlete is, you know, struggling with this
thing, or this person is struggling with that
disease risk, or whatever it is.
When we un- wanna understand our
diversity, we have to break it
down, I think, back to that kind of fundamental
beginning, and then it's a good way into it.
Why does this stuff even help?
Why does it even matter-
Yeah.
... that
we're thinking about genetics, as an example, wrong? We gave
the example earlier of why it mattered for GFR.
Mm-hmm.
But
can you think of any exa- examples of where
over-generalizing by population,
or perhaps maybe
not thinking about the uniqueness of that
individual population appropriately-
Yeah.
... matters. Like, what are the practical
implications of these mistakes-
Oh.
... outside of sociocultural, like...
Uh, here's a fun example, and we can do a couple
of these, but here's a fun one.
Uh, I was working in Northern Kenya, uh, when we first
started working on, on that project
with a community, uh, called the
Dosniq, which is a traditio-
Oh, perfect. Great.
Yeah.
Great. Let's, yes.
Traditional, uh, pa- pastoralists, these folks,
you know, they live with their
herds, goats and cattle and, and camels. Um,
and we started this project. We, we got in
the community, and of course, this is community-based
work. We, we met with, uh, community leaders.
We met with the health clinic folks. We wanted
to, before we started, to make
sure we were talking to everybody and getting everybody on
board, and this is something we all wanted to do.
One of the folks we talked to was this, uh, German
charity that was there to try to, um,
to, to, you know, reduce malnutrition in this group. And
so they're giving food supplementation
to moms with little kids to try to fix what
they saw as malnutrition.
Um, and so we, um,
we met with this guy from the German
charity, me and, and our, my
Kenyan colleague, Rosemary, who's wonderful. And, you
know, this guy's like, "Look, man,
it's really bad.
Malnutrition. 60% of the kids here
are, are malnourished." That's scary.
Obviously, that's a tragedy.
And so we thought, "Oh, gosh, okay,
that's important to know."
And then, um-... but you go out into the community, you go
around the villages, and that's not what you see.
What you see is kids running around, playing, happy,
laughing. And if there's- if malnourished,
y- you know, if- if undernourishment is that big of an issue,
you should also see issues with fertility.
Mm-hmm.
You don't see that. You see big families. Um, folks
are active, healthy, doing their thing.
That's strange. How- how do we square
the circle on that?
And it turns out, um,
you know, we, uh, were talking to the
health clinic about this.
And they had, in their records, partly d- with this
charity, they- they had been doing this.
They had been collecting heights and weights
for children in that, uh,
community, the Dostonic community, for years and
years. And they had, uh, you know,
hundreds, I think a couple thousand of
measurements of- of- of
kids' heights and weights from birth up through,
you know, up through childhood.
Science gold.
Wonderful. It's so awesome, right?
Yeah. Everything you could ever hope for.
Yeah. So what we were able to do is
basically make a Dostonic community
growth curve, right? What the Germans
guys had been doing
is, they'd been taking heights and weights of kids and
they'd been plotting them against WHO standards.
Oh, there you go. There you go.
Right?
Yep.
And the assumption there is that kids everywhere across
the globe all grow exactly the same.
Bingo.
The kids in the Dostonic community
were doing a really cool thing, actually. They would
start off normal height and weight.
They would kind of fall off the growth
curve a little bit,
eh, around year one. But then around year two,
their heights would shoot up.
They were taller than the a- global
standard, actually.
But because of that, their height for their
weight, that ratio looked
thin.
Way off, yeah.
Did they physically look ill? Did
they physically-
They don't look, they don't look
ill, but even-
Just lanky.
... the folks, they just tall and thin. It's just, it's
just the body build in that population.
And so, um, the German charity,
where they had their hearts in the right
place, they wanted to help, but you are never gonna get that
popula- those kids to look like, you know,
WHO standard kids. 'Cause they are in- in that
population, and that's, you know,
the alleles that- that- that promote a tall,
thin build are really common.
That's an adaptation in that part
of the world for
dealing with really hot climates is it's incredibly
hot there. You're on the equator.
Um, being tall and thin is a way to- to
be able to thermoregulate better. That's been known for a
long time. We see that a- around the world.
Tall, thin body build tends to be more common in really hot
climates 'cause it's a way to dump heat.
Yeah, surface area, along, right?
Surface area, exactly. Yep.
Yeah.
Um, and so these kids were doing exactly what
their bodies were built to do.
Now, if you understand the way that height
works, just to pick a trait, and the
interplay of genetics and environment,
um,
then you can look at that and say, "Oh, that's the
system. Now I understand it." Now,
actually, now that you have a
Dostonic-specific
growth curve, now you could pick the kids
that really do need help.
Oh, yeah.
That's great. You could help them. You could
focus the help better. Um, and
I don't fault the German charity
for wanting to help.
Clearly.
But they were never gonna achieve. They
actually left. They- they
closed up shop and left because they thought, "We
can't solve this problem." Right?
Oh, no.
So there's a great example. If you don't
understand how the system works, you're
gonna make, you're gonna come to wrong
conclusions about how to help. You're gonna
come to wrong conclusions about,
um, about what's going on. You're gonna
flag the wrong people
for needing help. You're gonna, you're gonna
miss who does need help, you know?
All these things. Uh, so I think pragmatically
understanding how these systems work and how
genes and environment work together and how it's a s-
you know, it's a trait-by-trait thing.
You know, just because I know about their
growth curves doesn't m- mean I know about
anything else about them, by the way.
Right.
It d- mean, I don't know their heart
health or their, uh,
you know, mental health or anything like that.
It, those are different traits.
There is clearly need and value
in population level research.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, this is, again, your field.
Yeah.
At least your old field
on that.
What you're clearly arguing for, though, here, is at
least as I interpret it, is a move
closer towards precision.
Yeah.
Individualized.
Towards individualized, right?
Yeah.
How do we, in your words, square that circle? In other
words, how do we set up research, how do we
think about research on the population level?
Mm-hmm.
Because there are benefits we can get from that, that we
can't get from, you know, individualized-
Oh, for sure.
... single recent.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
How do we get the best out of both? How do we
use population-level research so that we can be the most
informed and then also not make these mistakes-
Yeah.
... like we are currently doing
with basically
everything in genetics, in terms of... And to be
clear, what I'm saying there is,
if you're making nutrition or
exercise decisions based on
your genetic testing-
Yeah.
... and I think you've laid out a compelling argument
that that's probably quite short-sighted-
Yeah.
... to be kind.
How do we do this? How do we think about it?
What I think this kind of work are used for
is
a few different things. First of all, I
think if we had better
fluency, and I think if you learned your
biology and how these things worked
in the same way that you learn social studies
and, you know, English lit-
Mm-hmm.
... and all these things, I think that this is
part of the general fluency that we
expect kids to- to come out of high schools with or out of
colleges with, that we would all be better consumers
of things like retail genetics. We'd all be better patients
with our doctors, because when they say,
"Here's how your kidney function looks,"
you'd say, "Wait a second."
Mm-hmm.
Right?
So I think it's, that's part of
what this kind of, of
new understanding of diversity and how our
bodies work, I think that's one,
you know, important avenue for that. In terms of how we
change the way we think about research,
here's what I would love to have. I
would love to see, um,
research that didn't, um, just
reiterate the same kind of
wrong classifications like we think, right?
Yeah.
I mean, I can tell you, if you do
NIH-based research-
Yep, yep.
... you're supposed to tell them how many Hispanic,
non-white His- n- non-black Hispanic, uh,
non-Hispanic whites, b- l- this is the
census categories, right?
Yep.
And then somehow those categories are used to interpret
results of your population-based data
in a way that we know
going into it is fundamentally
problematic. And, you know,
there's... (laughs) I'm not saying that we
don't wanna have diverse
cohorts. I'm saying the opposite, actually.
I- I... Okay, thank you.
Yeah.
Yes.
I'm saying the opposite. I'm saying that let's
treat, you know, let- let's
take these individual by individual.
If, um... And let's look at
trait-specific, uh,
for, you know, let's look at trait-specific physiology. Let's
look at those individual axes of variation.
Um,
it might be helpful to know
in your big population that folks who are Black in the
United States have these physiological outcomes.
Yeah.
But that's not telling you that
skin color does that
or that their genetics did that. That's
flagging that perhaps
their environment, because of, you know, all the
cultural baggage we have in the US,
are affecting physiologies that way. Let's,
let's understand it that way.
Um, so
I'm not... We, we need diverse research. We need
diverse research populations. But the way
that we handle it just has to be different.
Yeah. I actually... I love how
you frame that.
If I could throw a, uh, a little bit of an
analogy on the spot here on that-
Yeah.
... the way that I generally like
to think about
population-based data, and let's just keep
using that example. One
trait that you'll see pop up, we said earlier,
um, for Black, African American-
Mm-hmm.
... much higher rates of type 2 diabetes.
Much, generally higher rates of
obesity, right?
So what you're saying is population data
can shine a light on that.
Yeah.
And that allows us to say, "Hey, we need more focus. We
need more emphasis. We need more resources."
Yeah.
Does that
then tell you, if you're Black, there's something in
your physiology that makes you, uh,
have more diabetes? Maybe, maybe not. All it's simply saying
is there's something in the entire picture.
Yeah. That's a great example. An- another one, uh, is heart
disease, hypertension and heart disease.
Yep.
We know that, uh, Black folks, Native Americans, other
minorities have higher rates of hypertension
and heart disease, uh, than whites in the
US. That's... We know that.
Yeah.
For a long time, in the '80s, '90s, uh,
particularly the observation that we had higher rates of
hypertension among Black Americans was taken to
somehow mean-... interpreted it as, they
have a genetic predisposition
to hypertension.
I spent my graduate work in Memphis-
Yeah.
... in health science. I had to teach this.
And it's wrong.
Yeah.
Right? It is both true that that's,
that in the US, you know,
Black populations have higher rates of hypertension. It
is also true that if you (laughs) go
anywhere else that doesn't have a history
of racism, guess what?
Yeah.
They don't. And it's, um, same with
Native- Native Americans, uh,
have higher rates of cardiovascular
disease in the US.
Go to places where, um, uh, the hearty, the, the
healthiest hearts in the world
are in, um, Indigenous populations
in Bolivia. Right?
So, and it's basically a very similar,
you know, recent, uh, d-
uh, diaspora of those populations down into South Af- South
America. So you're talking about genetically
kind of similar populations, if you wanna
talk about it that way.
Right.
Um,
so
point being, um,
we take the wrong conclusions, we make the wrong
fixes, we learn the wrong lessons
when we don't understand how our bodies work
and how, why we become unique.
And to your point of the,
the German charity-
Yeah.
... this can be done well hearted.
Right? It's just not, uh,
again, potentially not focusing
the right lens-
That's right.
... and help and support-
Yeah.
... in the areas, 'cause we don't understand what the actual
rationale, what the reason, what the cause-
Yeah.
... is for some of these issues. So, on
the topic then of
diversity and physiology-
Yeah.
... right, we'll, we'll stick again to
our side of the equation.
How do we best think about that? What
is the best way we can
learn from it, make
better help-
Mm-hmm.
... better support, whether it's scientifically,
public health. I know you don't work in-
Yeah.
... areas of public health, but
what is the most appropriate way that we should at
lea- maybe start thinking about it, or
advocating for types of science?
Like, a- anything that's
the solution side of the equation, how should
we be better thinking about it?
Yeah. I think, uh, when we understand
the role o- of environment especially in a lot of
these, uh, health outcome, like d-
uh, diabetes risk, obesity risk, heart
disease risk, um, uh, I, I think
a kinda individualized approach and a
life course approach, because we're thinking about
environment over the lifespan here-
Yep.
... okay, um, points us to research
that's gonna focus on early
life experiences especially, getting those
environments right, right? Childhood is a really
important, obviously learning period for
your body's physiology. Um,
and, you know, I think
using, you know, w- when we see differences
among different communities in,
in health outcomes, not ascribing that to
some inherent issue there-
Mm-hmm.
... but, uh, flagging that as, usually when it's at the
population level, an environmental issue.
When we see individual differences,
well now, we can
ask, "Okay, what is it about your individual physiology
that's, that's, that we need to tweak?"
That's a move towards an, you know, kind of
precision medicine that I don't think,
you know, uh, I don't have all the
answers there yet.
Of course.
I don't know that anybody does.
No.
But that's, we can focus more on the
individual that way and, and hopefully
do, do a better job.
It's, again, I'll never get over this
interesting, what I feel like is a juxtaposition of what
your academic background (laughs) is-
Yeah.
... and the fact that you're now
arguing so heavily for,
I'm sure it feels like it's seamless and is the
same thing, but I'm like, finally.
(laughs)
Yes, a person that's telling us all
about how we can learn
from studying one tribe-
Yeah.
... 1,000 years ago is now getting it here.
Do you feel like
your time
as,
I don't know, were you technically an
EMT? I know you were-
Oh, yeah.
... in that stuff, like-
That's right, yeah, about-
Do you feel like that-
... three or four years.
Yeah. Um,
is that, is that a part of this
here? Is that why
you're seeing this? Is that how you're
able to kinda zoom back and
look at population level stuff as well as
the individual person?
Yeah. Yeah.
I feel like when I read that, and when I
knew that about you, I'm like, "This has gotta be in there
somewhere that's driving this equation."
Yeah. I, um,
I think that my time as an EMT, uh,
was motivated by
two big things. You know, it's, you
never know, you,
you sort of, we, we tell our stor- stories about
why we do things after the fact.
Yeah.
Right? Um,
so I don't know if I would've articulated this as an 18 or
19-year-old taking that EMT class at Penn State
when I learned how to do this stuff. Um,
I think it, it really hit two
buttons for me. One was the human physiology side
and just seeing, you know, medical,
the, the medical world play out, you know,
in practical terms (laughs) with a, a
patient that you're taking
care of and understanding the body that way.
That was, that's super cool.
Yeah.
Uh, but the other thing was, you know,
medicine and especially emergency medicine happens
behind closed doors for most of us.
Yep.
We don't get to see it firsthand. Certainly as,
growing up, I didn't get to see it. My
parents weren't doctors or
anything like that.
And so, to kind of pull the curtain to the side
and understand how that, uh,
high intensity
world worked and just understand how the world
worked a little bit. And, and that was
a draw I couldn't... I think that
was the biggest draw.
I wanted to know what happened to the
back of the ambulance, man.
Yeah.
You know? I wanted to know what happens
when you pull up on a
car wreck and you have to make decisions
right now about how you're gonna
treat the patient, keep the scene safe,
get the, you know, and, and
the immediacy of it, the fact that it's something that
most of the w- that I never got to see
growing up, um,
yeah, it wa- the, that was the draw. And, and, you
know, the patient care obviously, and the,
that's obviously a big thing too. But I think
the, that was the big draw for me.
Did you have a love of physiology before that, or
was that what jumped it off a lot?
I, I think
that and, um, the, the anthropology classes I was taking
were very kind of biologically focused.
Yeah.
So that, that combined elements of that, you
know, what you're learning from the
medical context in an EMT book and then the, the
evolutionary perspective on it in my classes.
I think that, uh, I, you know, I haven't
really put it together like
that before, but I think that's right.
I think that's kind of
was this cool synergy as I was figuring out
what I wanted to do with my life.
What do you have coming up next in that? Uh,
you were talking earlier about some of the
projects you've got going on.
Yeah.
What, where's the next
question you, we talked about a bunch-
Yeah.
... of things you could answer.
What's on the immediate horizon for you right now?
What are you most interested in next?
Well, we have a really exciting project happening right now,
uh, two actually, trying to, to understand
metabolic ceilings. Um, you know, is that r- is there really a
cap on what the body can do? And if there is,
how do we push it? What happens
when you push it? Uh,
and so we've got one study going on right
now looking at, at pregnancy
and looking at, uh, female athletes through
pregnancy that are maintaining really
high activity workloads to sort
of see how that
pushes the body around and energy
expenditures and all that, all the
follow-on things that happen with that.
Yeah.
Um, that's a super exciting project that hopefully we'll
have out in the next, uh, year or so.
Um, we have a project looking at ultra
marathon runners, asking, um,
you know, outside of the pregnancy context, just people
who are just pushing their bodies to the
extreme, what does that look like
physiologically, metabolically. Um,
and that's worked, we're, I'm doing with Drew
Best in Massachusetts, uh, and
that's been really fun. So, those are kind of
that, that avenue of research. Um,
we wanna get work
going trying to look at organ metabolic rates and
how those might juggle and change-
Mm-hmm.
... um, in the face of, uh, lifestyle change, in
the face of different interventions.
Um, that's really early days, and I,
I'm hoping to get that
going. We'd love to know, uh, in that
same kind of, you know,
distant horizon is, uh, looking at life
course changes in, in
childhood and old age, how metabolic rates change.
And then, you know, we have a bunch of
projects right now looking at, uh, i- in different
communities. We have one looking at, at
health, uh, cardiometabolic health in, in, uh, in
pastors, in clergy, in Western North Carolina.
Oh, okay.
You know, they, there's a, they have a, we were asked to,
to help out on this grant. Um, there's a s-
kind of higher rates of, of cardiometabolic disease,
diabetes and stuff with this population
than we'd like to see. Higher than sort of
background, other, other folks in
that, those same
communities. We wanna understand what it is,
what is it about the, the
challenges of that job, psychological-... physical
activity, diet that are pushing, you know,
you know,
health outcomes where we don't
wanna see them.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and we're working abroad still. So, we
have the work in, in Kenya, um,
other collaborations around the world. So yeah, you know,
it's a busy, uh, it's a, it's a full plate.
Yeah, you're not slowing down at all, in
addition to writing books-
Yeah.
... and all those things.
If someone
would've
been as fascinated as I am-
(laughs)
... in this conversation, I, I really, really
thoroughly enjoyed it, and they're thinking
to themselves, "Okay, great,
how can I
better think about metabolism,
energy expenditure,
all these things?" Is there any other lessons
that you think people should glean that you
really want to emphasize-
Mm.
... or that they can pull from? Uh, you mentioned this
several times now, you're a natural teacher.
Mm-hmm.
Just talent-wise, and you also clearly have a passion for it.
So, how do we help connect this last dot for
people in saying like, "I really like what
people... I'd like for people to learn"?
Yeah.
Okay, so let's start with the metabolism thing. Um,
if people are trying to, you know,
optimize their health, change their body
composition, maybe maintain their body
composition, thinking about
meta- metabolism, I
emphasize that we should think about diet and exercise as
two different tools for two different jobs.
Yep.
I'm sure there's lots of crossover, but
diet's going to be your best tool, uh,
for maintaining weight
or getting your weight where you
need it to be.
Exercise is going to be your main tool for
everything else, right? Heart
health, mental health, muscle health.
Fill in the blanks, right?
Fill in the blanks.
Um,
now how do we connect that to this second
half of our conversation about
individualized approaches and diversity?
Uh, I think
you need to treat yourself as N of one
and understand that
there is a real broad range of, of possible diets
that might work best for you, possible
exercises that you're gonna get into
that y- you're gonna love more or less.
You know, your inv- individual environment and
genes, how those mesh together,
that's... Nobody has that same setup.
You know, you, you are unique. And so, um, I think the
one-size-fits-all approaches, I think
the kind of evangelistic, "You have to have this
diet approach," kind of thing,
give yourself a break, walk away from that and just ask,
"Okay, I'm gonna pay attention to myself,
and I'm gonna treat myself as N of one,"
because I... you are.
And, um, you can play around with what we know is out
there, be evidence-based. You know,
read, read good books, read good papers, or
listen to great podcasts,
and figure out what the evidence is out there and then
say, "Okay, I can, I can play with this,
uh, without putting myself in a
bucket of, 'Oh, I'm a
woman, and therefore this,' 'I'm a man, and therefore
that,' 'I'm this group or that group-"
This age, yeah.
"... on that group.'" You're N of one, so,
you know, go out a- and, and feel free to sort of
play with it that way. And, and,
you know, I think with that kind of an approach, first
of all, it lets you breathe a little bit
and have a little less stress about, "Oh,
I'm not doing it right."
Perfect, right.
Uh-
It's empowering. It should be more
empowering than-
I hope so.
... than, than not, right?
Yeah. And, uh, and then it also lets you explore and
find something that you love. I, you know,
I'm not a... I'm an anthropologist, I s- I
study people, and what I
can tell you is across the world, around the
world, if people don't love something,
it doesn't matter what, you know, culturally,
whatever, all the diversity, if people
don't love something, they're not
gonna stick with it.
People do what they love. They
always fall back to it.
And so if you can't find a lifestyle
approach that, that is gonna
really resonate with you, it's
not gonna matter
what it does physiologically, because it's not gonna
stick. So, I think that's... You know,
listen to yourself and, and be N of one,
because that's what you are.
If somebody wanted to do
something like this, and
they wanted to start learning more
about their metabolism-
Mm-hmm.
... and figuring out their daily energy
expenditure and things like that, uh,
what tools would you recommend? Where
should they start?
Yeah.
What options do people have if they want to
follow your advice there?
Yeah. Uh, well, I mean, you can go low tech,
you've got the bathroom scale.
Yep.
Right? And-
It's always the best place. (laughs)
It's not a bad place to start.
Yeah.
Uh, you know, if you're... And, and, you
know, we talked a little bit
in this conversation about
models versus data.
If your model is, "I'm on this diet, and I'm
eating at an energy deficit,"
but the s- the data say you're
not losing weight,
then I'm sorry, you're not eating... I mean,
you know, that's just it.
Yeah. Good data.
And, and so you gotta, you gotta kind of move
your... follow the data, not the model.
Um,
you know, there are lots of companies out
there that'll measure different aspects of
your health if you're into that.
Um, I would s-... If you wanna measure your energy
expenditures, I'm a, I'm a science advisor for a company
called Calorify. You can check them out,
uh, and, and do that.
Just tell us a little quickly about what
that is and how it works.
Oh, right, yeah. So, this is a really
cool, uh, company-
And, and full disclosure, I've used
it many times, uh,
I paid for it full price, no discount.
Okay.
So,
um, I've, I've used it quite often, but-
Awesome, yeah.
... what do we do with this?
Yeah, so, uh, this is a company
that was, uh...
So, the technique I talked about
earlier about how we measure
total energy expenditures, all the
calories you burn over, oh,
for, for 24 hours, um, the
technique we use is, uh,
called the doubly labeled water
method. It's an isotope
tracking method, and it's the gold standard for doing
those kind of measurements. And, uh,
until recently, there wasn't sort of a retail
way to do that. You couldn't just
get a measurement for yourself. You had to sign up
for a study or something like that.
Um, uh, Hari Mix, who's the, the founder of Calorify, and I was
there too to help get it off the ground, um,
I'm a science advisor for that company,
full disclosure, uh, they,
they wanted to, to make this sort of available to everybody.
And so you can check out Calorify and, um,
and, and, and get those measurements
yourself if you want.
Great. Fantastic.
What would you say to
somebody who
was concerned that they've been in a caloric
deficit for a long time, they have
been, uh, potentially whether they're
losing weight or not, but they're eating a really low amount
of calories, potentially they've lowered it.
Yeah.
They, they're weighing, they're
measuring, they're-
Mm-hmm.
... reasonably accurate in that, and
they've continued to reduce a couple of hundred calories,
it's been months and months and months.
Yeah.
Now they're concerned that they have
crashed their metabolism. They've-
Yeah.
... gone to the bo-... You-
People use-
Yeah.
We'll explain this thing differently, but-
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
...
is that a real thing? And if so,
what's happening there?
You can definitely see people's, like,
basal metabolic rates
go, get lower when they go on really, uh, you know,
kind of crash diet kind of things.
Yeah.
Um, as far as I know, I don't know of any evidence
that says it doesn't just recover
when you kind of go back to a, a, a more normal (laughs) amount
of food and, and a more normal exercise load.
Yeah.
Uh, and so I don't think anybody is
sort of forever damaged from whatever they tried
in the past, uh, you know. Um,
yeah. So again, let yourself off the hook a little
bit and it's, it's gonna be okay.
Yeah. Uh, I really, really appreciate you
coming halfway across... well-
(laughs)
... entirely across the country.
Yeah.
Um-
And I didn't run, I took an airplane.
You did?
So I... Yeah, I didn't do the marathon
a day thing for five
months. I, I just took... I just jumped
on a plane. I cheated.
I'm not gonna lie, I feel like that's
a little bit lazy.
It is.
Yeah.
I mean, you're... That's fair.
That's fair.
You got out here. But really appreciated it, I, I thoroughly
enjoyed it. I've been waiting a long time
for it, and I know people are gonna get
a ton out of this.
Um, if people want to follow along with your journey and
support and stuff, where can they do those things?
Uh, yeah, we're online, you can check out The
Ponser Lab, and we try to, uh,
you know, update how our projects are going.
Um, of course, we publish everything in
the scientific literature-
Sure.
... which isn't always easy to keep up
with, but it's there.
Um, and then, you know, check out, uh,
I guess you could check out my writing. We've
got a new book coming out, and,
uh, I'm sure there'll be more fun stuff to
tell the world about, so...
Uh, and then the foundation as well?
Oh, thanks for that. Yeah. Um, one of the things that
we've done working with the Hadza community
is to start, uh, a fi-... uh, to start a charity
that, that helps support their
population health to kind of give back, because
we've learned so much from them-
Yeah.
... um, we want to make sure we're... it's,
uh... we're giving back. And so
it's called Hadzafund, H-A-D-Z-A-F-U-N-D.org. Um, and
if folks want to support the Hadza
community, keep them strong and healthy, um,
they can go on there and make a donation.
Uh, it's always appreciated.
Really appreciate you coming out. I learned a ton,
and I know people are gonna respond
really positively to this. So,
thank you so much.
You bet. Thanks for the invitation. It was
a really fun conversation.
Thank you for joining for today's episode.
To learn more about Herman,
follow along with his
books, social media, laboratory, and other resources,
please check the show notes for direct links.
Thank you for joining for today's episode.
My goal, as always, is to share exciting scientific
insights that help you perform at your best.
If the show resonates with you, and you want to
help ensure this information remains
free and accessible to anyone in the world, there are a few
ways that you can support. First, you can
subscribe to the show on YouTube,
Spotify, and Apple.
And on Apple and Spotify, you can leave us
up to a five-star review.
Subscribing and leaving a review really does help us a
lot. Also, please check out our sponsors.
This show would not exist without them
and their exceptional products and services.
Finally, you can share today's episode with a
friend who you think would enjoy it.
If you have any content questions or suggestions, please put
those in the comments section on YouTube.
I really do try my best to read them all
and to see what you have to say. I
use my Instagram and X
profiles also exclusively for scientific
communication, so those are great
places to follow along for more learning. My handle is
@doctorandygalpin on both platforms.
We also have an email newsletter that distills all of our
episodes and the most actionable takeaways.
We have newsletters on how to improve
fitness and VO2 max,
how to build muscle and strength,
and much more.
To subscribe to the newsletter, just go to
performpodcast.com and click Newsletter.
It's completely free, and we do not share your email
with anybody. Thank you for listening.
And never forget, in the famous
words of Bill Bowerman,
"If you have a body, you are an
athlete." (instrumental music)